<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lama-sabachthani, or, Cry of the Son of God useful at all times, especially for Passion Week, and at all other times  for a devout and pious soul, in its nearest approaches and addresses to its Saviour, before and after it comes to be an actual partaker of the body  and blood of its Redeemer.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L205A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41448</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355370</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355370</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110425</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48436)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110425)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1742:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Lama-sabachthani, or, Cry of the Son of God useful at all times, especially for Passion Week, and at all other times  for a devout and pious soul, in its nearest approaches and addresses to its Saviour, before and after it comes to be an actual partaker of the body  and blood of its Redeemer.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[10], 134 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw. Jones, for Samuel Lowndes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: The Cry of the Son of God.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Passion --  Meditations.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110425:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Lama-ſabachthani,</hi> OR, CRY OF THE Son of GOD; Uſeful at all Times, eſpecially <hi>For PASSION Week.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND At all other Times for a <hi>Devout</hi> and <hi>Pious Soul,</hi> in its neareſt Approaches and Addreſſes to its <hi>Saviour,</hi> before and after it comes to be an Actual Partaker of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of its <hi>Redeemer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Edition,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Edw. Jones,</hi> for <hi>Samuel Lowndes,</hi> againſt <hi>Exeter-Change</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:110425:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110425:2"/>
            <head>To Her moſt Pious and Sacred MAJESTY Queen MARY, The Author moſt Humbly Offers and Dedicates the enſuing <hi>Enchiridion</hi> of a Crucify'd Saviour.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen I conſider the unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible Honour I lately had of being frequently a partaker with You at the Throne of Grace, in Your Chappel-Devotion at the <hi>Hague;</hi> Where, obſerving Your great Strength and Zeal of true Piety, accompanied with a perfect Stability of Humility, Meekneſs, and Lowlineſs of Spirit, as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Follower, and Imitator of our
<pb facs="tcp:110425:3"/>Dear Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, whilſt on Earth; it ſtruck ſuch a Dint upon me,<note place="margin">As <hi>St. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> ſays, melted down his Soul into Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> and enforc'd ſuch a Love of Religion in me, that made me inſpir'd to that height and Ecſtacy of Devotion, and Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Thought, that did not only, as it were, withdraw my Soul from all Commerce with the Senſes, but in a manner ſeparate it a while from the Body: And made it, with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> to have Antipaſts of Heaven, and a fruition of Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Enjoyments.</p>
            <p>Such Raptures, Elevations, and Influences of Anticipated Glory, as the Apoſtle had, had the Diſciples of our Saviour, whilſt their Great Lord and Maſter was Predicting and Communicating his Paſſion to be an abiding Commemoration of himſelf amongſt them, after his Aſcenſion into Glory, as it is largely
<pb facs="tcp:110425:3"/>ſet forth by our Saviour himſelf throughout the <hi>6th</hi> Chapter of <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as it was obſerv'd of <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of his Brethren, in the Transfiguration of our Saviour on the Mount, that when he Pray'd earneſtly to his Father, the Faſhion of his Countenance was alter'd, which did beget immediately in them, ſuch a Participation of Raptures, and Ejaculations, that made them very unwilling to relinquiſh the Place, where they had enjoy'd ſuch a Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fical Preſence.</p>
            <p>The like have I perceiv'd in Your Majeſties Countenance, as if it ſpake aloud the very Language of Your Divine Soul, that made mine always wiſh, in its Publick Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to live in the Preſence of ſo Great and ſo Glorious an Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar.</p>
            <p>No leſs perfect are all theſe Coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Qualifications in Your ever
<pb facs="tcp:110425:4"/>Ador'd and Dearly beloved Siſter; to enumerate them again were but Tautology; they are all ſo eſſentially compact in You both, that modeſtly and juſtly You are the Glory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe. The Hypoſtatick Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of Heaven having decreed it from all Eternity, that You Two ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d be Leaders and Patterns to all Sincere and Devout Subjects and Chriſtians, in all Virtue, Piety, and Holineſs, and that they be cloſe Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators and Followers of You, as You are of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This makes it tranſcendently the Felicity of all Humble, Pious Souls, to have Two ſuch Matchleſs Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Angels walk before us, and to be eminent for God in Your Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, as the aforeſaid <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Anna,</hi> the Mother of Jeſus, and Propheteſs of our Lord.</p>
            <p>How much more Glorious muſt the Proteſtant Religion neceſſarily appear in You, Madam, now You
<pb facs="tcp:110425:4"/>are, by the All-wiſe Providence of the Great God, moſt happily arriv'd at the Zenith of Sovereignty, whoſe Sovereign Beams have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy diſpers'd all thoſe Clouds and Miſts, (nay, Storms and Hurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans) of <hi>Popery,</hi> that of late had like to have ſubverted and over-whelm'd theſe Nations into a Bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Deluge by Maſſacre and Murder, had not God reſerv'd Your Majeſty for ſuch a day as This, and brought You ſafe through the dangers of the Seas, and plac'd Your Royal Perſon with King <hi>William</hi> on the Imperial Throne of Your Anceſtors, whoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Magnanimity and Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the Omnipotent Power of the Almighty, hath procur'd this re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment for us again; That when all our hopes were ſinking in the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn of Deſpair, God was pleas'd through him, by a ſtupendious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, to reſtore us again, without the tedious and cruel Sieges of War
<pb facs="tcp:110425:5"/>or Blood, to a Proteſtant Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>This is the only cauſe, that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldens me to preſent to You the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Meditations and Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations of the Agony and Crucifixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, Entituled, The <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſa-bachthani,</hi> or, <hi>Cry of the Son of God,</hi> wherein I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd, as ſuccinctly, and as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuouſly, as poſſibly I could, to ſet forth every Action and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of the Chief Prieſts, Scribes, Elders, and Soldiers, towards their accompliſhing of their wicked De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in perfecting of the ſo much hunger'd for Crucifixion of our Dear Lord and Saviour.</p>
            <p>How he was hurry'd and carry'd from one Place, Court, and Council, to another, Spit on and Buffeted in one, Array'd and Rob'd in another, Scourg'd and Crown'd with Thorns in another, mock'd and derided in
<pb facs="tcp:110425:5"/>all, but acquitted and diſcharg'd by none, and yet not found guilty of Death in any.</p>
            <p>I have follow'd the Evangeliſts as cloſe as I could, and have rank'd them as well as I am able, in ſo ſmall a thing, and have made the rough Draught as like the Original, as I can poſſible, in ſuitable Expreſſions, and earneſtly beg of God it may pleaſe all, and diſpleaſe none, being all Divine Truths.</p>
            <p>I moſt humbly preſent it to Your Majeſty, hoping it may receive a Candid and free Acceptation from You. It will lye in a little Room in Your Cloſet, and at the Table of the Lord, being more fitted for the Heart of a Devout and Pious Soul, than Voluminous, therefore may be as the Viand of the Soul in its near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Addreſſes to its Saviour, before, and after it comes to be an actual partaker of the Body and Blood of a Redeemer, whom I have end a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd
<pb facs="tcp:110425:6"/>to Delineate as well as I am able, in ſo ſmall a Tract, in the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt extremity of his Crucifixion; in his Agony and Bloody Sweat, on his Croſs and Paſſion; in his Death and Burial, and there left his moſt precious Body in the Grave, with Holy Angels, to attend his Call: I may hereafter preſume to write of his Glorious Reſurrection and Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion alſo, if I can find my weak En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours are in any degree uſeful, according to the Pious and Honeſt Intention of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Majeſties moſt Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and for ever moſt Devoted Humble Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> Anonymus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110425:6"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Lama-ſabachthani:</hi> OR, THE CRY OF THE Son of GOD.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>HEAR, O Heavens, and give Ear, O Earth, for the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi> O, what is this I hear? The Voice of the Son of God in the grievous Agony of his Soul, juſt breathing out his laſt, and crying to his God; nay, his Father
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110425:7"/>to ſuſtain and comfort him; either, O Holy Father, take from me this bitter Cup of Vinegar and Gaul of thy high Diſpleaſure, or elſe forſake me not in the time of my drinking this bitter Portion.</p>
            <p>Where is the Cry of the Son of God, the Saviour of the World? O where? Where? My diſtracted Soul, Where? Where ſhall I run? Where ſhall I fly, to find my Saviour? Whom ſhall I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of? Where ſhall I go? Whom ſhall I find to direct my perplexed Soul?<note place="margin">Fleſh.</note> It's dark, ſtormy, and tempeſtuous. If it were never ſo dark and diſmal, I will go. I cannot longer ſtay. Thou art warm and ſafe in Bed, and within doors, why ſhouldeſt thou diſturb thy ſelf? Peace, lye ſtill, and take thy reſt: I may lye ſtill, and ſlumber a little, but I cannot reſt. <hi>I ſleep, but my Heart waketh.</hi> Hark I Hark again! <hi>It is the Voice of my Beloved, that cryeth out,</hi> and he knocketh as he paſſeth by,<note place="margin">Chriſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th by to the Garden of <hi>Gethſemane.</hi>
               </note> to ſee whether I will receive him, and let him in: I hear him ſpeak: <hi>Open to me, my Siſter, my
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110425:7"/>Love, my Dove, my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled, for my Head is filled with Dew, and my Locks with the Drops of the Night.</hi> Lord! What's the matter? What makes him abroad now? What's the matter? I am ſure, more than ordinary; I will riſe and let him in. <hi>Thou haſt put off thy Clothes; how canſt thou put them on</hi> in the dark? Moreover, <hi>thou haſt waſh'd thy Feet; why ſhould'ſt thou defile them again?</hi> I ſtand not upon theſe Curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of my ſinful Fleſh, that muſt e're long crumble in the Duſt. <hi>My Beloved hath put in his band by the bole of the Door, and my Bowels are troubled for him;</hi> I cannot reſt; I muſt and will riſe.</p>
            <p>I have opened the Door to my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, but he is withdrawn, and is gone: My Soul even faileth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me.<note place="margin">The Rude Multitude perſuing our Saviour.</note> I hear a confuſed Noiſe at a diſtance. I cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led after the Noiſe, but he gave me no anſwer; and I have ſought for him about the door, but cannot find him; well, I will after him. I ſtand not upon the exactneſs of Dreſs, nor the danger of the Night. I will along the Street, and, as near as I can, follow. A truly gracious Soul,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110425:8"/>touch'd once with the love of God, will follow him at his Call, and no ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard or difficulty can obſtruct or hinder its eager purſuit after its dear <hi>Jeſu,</hi> the good Shepherd of its Soul. <hi>My Sheep hear my Voice, and they follow me,</hi> John 10.3, 4.</p>
            <p>Pardon me, if I here make a little digreſſion,<note place="margin">Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits the care of his ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered Flock to <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </note> and anticipate the words of our Saviour to <hi>Peter.</hi> Happy art thou, O <hi>Peter,</hi> that the Saviour of Souls deems thee worthy to be his deputed Shepherd, and commits his Flock to thy vigilant Care, before he left the World; they were near and dear to him, they were the purchas'd of his Soul; <hi>He carrieth his Lambs</hi> (his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Lambs) <hi>in his Arms, and gently leadeth thoſe that are with Young;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Peter,</hi> you very well know the value I have for them, and the belief I have in you: Take care, I ſay, to <hi>feed my little Flocks beſide,</hi> or near, <hi>the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd's Tents. Peter,</hi> be not angry that I ask you again and again. <hi>Do you love me? Do you love me more than all? Yea, Lord, thou know'ſt that I love thee. Then
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110425:8"/>feed my Sheep, feed my Lambs,</hi> and ſee that none of them be loſt: I know all their Names, and I bear them all in my Heart, as the High-Prieſt did the Tribes in his Breaſt, and I carry them all to Heaven with me, whither I am now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring with all ſpeed, after I have eaten with you. <hi>Where I am, there they ſhall be alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And it came to paſs, when Jeſus had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed all theſe ſayings, be ſaid unto his Diſciples, Ye know, that after two days is the Feaſt of the Paſſover,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels his being apprehended.</note> 
               <hi>and the Son of Man is betrayed to be crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Then aſſembled together all the Chief Prieſts, and the Scribes, and the Elders of the People, unto the Palace of the High-Prieſts, which is called</hi> Caiphas, <hi>and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted, that they might take Jeſus by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty, and kill him, but not on the Feaſt day, leſt there be an uproar among the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> Matth. <hi>26.</hi> For <hi>Annas</hi> the High-Prieſt had, at that time, agreed with <hi>Judas</hi> to betray his Maſter, and had given him thirty pieces of Silver out of the Treaſury, and <hi>Judas</hi> with them craftily concluded, it ſhould be in the Night, for better ſecurity, and freer from diſturbance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:110425:9"/>Now the <hi>firſt day of the Feaſt of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaven'd Bread being come, the Diſciples came to Jeſus, and ask'd him, Where he pleas'd they eat the Paſſover? Jeſus ſaith unto them, Go, two of you into the City to ſuch a Man's Houſe, and tell him, The Maſter ſaith, My time is at hand: I will keep the Paſſover at thy Houſe this night. Accordingly they went, and made ready the Paſſover, and when Even was come, he ſate down with the Twelve, and as they did eat, he ſaid, Verily I ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that one of you will betray me; and they were exceeding ſorrowful, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan every one of them to ſay into him, Lord, Is it I? And he anſwered and ſaid, The ſame that dippeth his hand with me in the Diſh, ſhall betray me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Son of Man goeth, as it is written of him, but wo unto that Man, by whom the Son of Man is betrayed. It had been good for that man, if he had never been born; Judas,</hi> being near unto our Lord, and hearing this ſharp precaution, and the fore-knowledge that his Maſter had of his deſign, would ſeem, before the reſt of the Diſciples, to be as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent of the thing, as any of them that were ſo exceedingly troubled, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110425:9"/>therefore ask'd his Maſter, <hi>Is it I?</hi> Not thinking that Jeſus could, or, if he could, that he would, point-blank charge him with it; yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, his Maſter ſaid, <hi>Thou haſt ſaid:</hi> Now <hi>Judas</hi> was ſtartled at all this, yet, for covetouſneſs, and lucre of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, having already receiv'd it, would not go back.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>they were eating, Jeſus rook Bread, and bleſſed it, and brake it, and gave it to his Diſciples, and ſaid, Take, eat, this is my Body which is broken for you, this do in remembrance of me; and he took the Cup in like manner, and gave thanks, and gave it to them, ſaying, Drink ye all of it, for this is the Blood of the New Teſtament, ſhed for many for the remiſſion of Sins. But I ſay unto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22.20.</note> 
               <hi>I will not henceforth drink of the fruit of the Vine, till I drink it new with you in my Fathers Kingdom. And when they had ſung an Hymn, they went out. Jeſus ſaith unto them, Ye ſhall all be offended becauſe of me this night; For it is written, I will ſmite the Shepherd, and the Sheep ſhall be ſcatter'd. Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Tho' all be offended, yet will not I.</hi> Jeſus ſaith
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110425:10"/>unto him, <hi>Before the Cock crow twice, thou ſhalt deny me thrice. Peter</hi> ſaith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, I will be with thee, my Lord, both in Life and Death.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Ittai</hi> ſaid to <hi>David, As the Lord liveth, and as my Lord the King liveth, ſurely in what place the Lord my King ſhall be, whether in Death or Life, even there alſo will thy Servant be,</hi> 2 Sam. 15.19, 20, 21.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Ruth</hi> ſaid to her Mother-in-Law <hi>Naomi, Entreat me not to leave thee, nor to return from following after thee, for where thou goeſt, I will go, where thou lodgeſt, I will lodge, they People ſhall be my People, and thy God, my God; where thou dyeſt, I will dye, and there will I be buried. The Lord do ſo to me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ruth</hi> 1.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>and much more alſo, if ought but Death part thee and me.</hi> Saith <hi>Peter,</hi> So is my Heart knit to thee, dear Maſter. Peter, <hi>I know that thou loveſt me,</hi> and therefore <hi>Satan hath a deſire to ſift thee,</hi> and try thee, as he did <hi>Job;</hi> but <hi>I have prayed for thee, that thy Faith fail thee not,</hi> Job ch. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:110425:10"/>Then Jeſus goeth to <hi>Gethſemane,</hi> for his <hi>hour being now come, and taketh with him only three of his Diſciples,</hi> Peter, James, <hi>and</hi> John, they being the three appointed by their Lord and Maſter to ſee the ſaid Tragedy. <hi>Peter,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his chief Diſciple, to whom he ſhould commend the Care of his Church, which e're long was to ſuffer great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution. <hi>James,</hi> the laſt of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, yet the firſt that was to ſuffer for the Goſpel's ſake, and therefore moſt fit to ſee his Maſter betray'd, that his Maſter's meekneſs and patience in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring might be a pattern and example to him, who e're long muſt follow. And <hi>John,</hi> the moſt beloved Diſciple of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> whom <hi>Peter</hi> ask'd his Maſter; But of this Diſciple <hi>that lean'd on thy Breaſt at Supper-time,</hi> and firſt ſaid, <hi>Whom it is,</hi> Lord, <hi>that ſhall betray thee? What ſhall this man do?</hi> Saith <hi>Jeſus</hi> to him, <hi>If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee? Follow thou me.</hi> Yet, moſt Holy <hi>Jeſus,</hi> thou, that knoweſt all things, probably for ſuch-like Reaſons took theſe only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with thee, and ſaid unto them, <hi>My Soul is exceeding ſorrowful, even
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110425:11"/>unto Death: Tarry ye here, and watch with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And be went a little farther, and fell on his face to the ground; and prayed, O my Father, if it be poſſible, let this Cup paſs from me, nevertheleſs, not as I will, but as thou wilt;</hi> For tho' <hi>Jeſus,</hi> as Man, fear'd the approaching danger that was coming upon him, and juſt now ready to ſeize him, and therefore was, in this great Agony, <hi>sweating drops of Blood</hi> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to the ground; yet, as God, it was mutually agreed upon already in the great Court of Heaven, between his Father and Himſelf, that this was the only way could be found out for the Redemption of fallen Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For God ſo loved the World, that he have bis only begotten Son to death for it, that whoſoever believeth in him, might not periſh, but have everlaſting life;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as God, God-Man was reſolv'd to fulfil his Father's Will. <hi>Father, all things are poſſible to thee, but if this Cup ſhall not paſs, Thy Will be done,</hi> O Holy Father.</p>
            <p>And <hi>he cometh to his Diſciples again a ſecond time, but, finding them aſleep,</hi> ſaith to <hi>Peter, Simon, Why ſleepeſt thou?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110425:11"/>Could not you watch with me one hour?</hi> You know what I have Pray'd for alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. <hi>Watch and Pray,</hi> now, <hi>leſt you enter into Temptation. The Spirit indeed, Peter,</hi> I know, <hi>is willing, but the Fleſh it weak.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Holy <hi>Jeſu,</hi> what Sweetneſs and Love is this of thine, that even at the very minute that thou wert to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed, thou ſhouldeſt pity the Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of thy Servants, that even now thou hadſt commanded to <hi>Watch and Pray,</hi> and yet, even in this very laſt minute, found them ſleeping; one would rather have thought, thou ſhouldſt have been extremely angry with them, but, inſtead of that, thou excuſeſt their fault. This ſweetneſs, and this behaviour of thine, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of Humane Infirmities, <hi>will draw all Men to thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt knew at this time, that ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he was to ſuffer for the Sins of the whole World, in what nature and kind ſoever, as to the aggravation and hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs of them; and might he not then very well paſs by the Infirmities of his beloved Diſciples, when he knew, that their Sleep proceeded partly from their Trouble and Sorrow.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:110425:12"/>
               <hi>Jeſus leaveth them again, and goeth a Third time, and prayeth more earneſtly, and cryeth louder,</hi> and ſweateth much greater drops of Blood than before. <hi>O Righteous Father, if it be poſſible, let this Cup paſs from me, but yet, Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy Will be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O my Soul! where am I?<note place="margin">The devout Soul hearing the Cry, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after our Saviour.</note> Where? <hi>O Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men!</hi> Where am I? <hi>Where is my Beloved?</hi> Where is he gone aſide? My Soul melteth away. I hear his Cry, but I know not where to find him. I am ſure, it's his Voice, but I know not which way to go; the dark Night hath conceal'd him from my Sight, but not from my Heart: His Cry pierceth my Soul. O good Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men! Dear Watch-men! <hi>Where ſhall I find him, whom my Soul loveth, and longeth for?</hi> Hark! Hark! He cryes louder and louder. Help! Help! What's the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, dear Saviour? I cannot find thee; I know not where thou art; ſometimes thy Voice ſeemeth near, and ſometime farther off; ſometimes on this ſide os me, and ſometimes on that; ſometimeſ before me, and ſometimes behinds
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110425:12"/>whether from the Walls and Vaults of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or whether from the Brook <hi>Cedron</hi> or from the Trees in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, or from all theſe places together, theſe uncertain Sounds and Eccho's come, I know not; they perplex me, and confound me. I cannot find thee. I know not where thou art. Direct me, Lord, the way. I know, thou art <hi>the Way, the Truth, and the Light;</hi> but I know not where to find thee, thus at a diſtance, this dark Night. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect me, Lord, the way. <hi>Speak,</hi> Dear Lord, and <hi>thy Servant heareth.</hi> My Soul is attentive to thy Call, but I am not able to bear longer thy Cry. O quickly! Dear Saviour, quickly! Tell me but where I ſhall find thee. What No Directions yet, Dear <hi>Jeſu!</hi> O! dear Watchmen, for the Lord's ſake, for my dear Saviour's ſake! for my! poor Soul's ſake! tell me, <hi>tell me, for why ſhould I be as one that turneth aſide from the Flocks of thy Companions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saith the Watchmen, we cannot lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger endure to hear thee cry, and make ſuch moan. We ſuppoſe you may find him in or about the Garden of <hi>Geth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemane.</hi> We believe the Cry comes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110425:13"/>that way. We can hear it eaſily, but it is beyond our Bounds; we muſt not, nor dare not, go beyond our own Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts, eſpecially without the Gates of the City, and more eſpecially when there is ſo great a Noiſe and Tumult abroad; we know not, how ſoon there may be an uproar here, and therefore we muſt keep our Poſts upon Life and Death, let what will come of it; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſome of us would go along with you, to direct you, and light you along; but that is the way. I, but are you ſure the Cry and Noiſe comes from thence? That we are not ſure; but this we are ſure of, That a great Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Multitude of Soldiers ran that way, and ſaid nothing, but ran apace, whiſpering amongſt themſelves: Some carry'd with them Swords, others car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd Staves and Halbards, and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles and Lanthorns in their hands. We believe it's ſome great matter they are gone about, they carry it with ſo much ſecrecy, as they go along; but we cannot think it is for <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,</hi> becauſe we did ſee <hi>Judas,</hi> one of the Lord's Diſciples, amongſt them. Hark! the Cry is louder indeed now.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110425:13"/>I don't know what to think of it, but there's the ready way.</p>
            <p>O, my dear Lord, have I found thee! What, in Blood,<note place="margin">Soul.</note> in the depth of thine Agony, with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent Sweats, and drops of Blood run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down thy Face, and crying to thy thy Father too? What's the matter, dear Lord? Speak quickly to my Soul, or elſe I ſink and dye; I cannot longer forbear, having run my ſelf quite out of breath with thy grievous Cry. Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous indeed it muſt needs be, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Son of God ſweat, and cry, and bleed thus.</p>
            <p>I am ſtriving and ſtrugling, praying,<note place="margin">Chriſt.</note> ſweating, and bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for thy Salvation, with my Father's Wrath and Indignation; but thy Sins are ſo great, ſo heinous, and grievous, that nothing will ſatisfie him but thy Eternal Death, which thou, alas, art never able to endure, the Wrath and Indignation of an incenſed and enraged God againſt thee. I have been pleading and interceding with my Heavenly Father, offering up ſtrong Prayers and Tears for thy Atonement; but all will not do: A Life muſt be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110425:14"/>and I have offered my own, if nothing elſe will ſatisfie. <hi>Not my Will, but thy Will be done.</hi> It muſt be ſo, and the unalterable and uncontrouled De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the Almighty muſt be fulfilled, and I come willingly, <hi>as in the Volume of the Book it is written of me, to do thy Will, O God;</hi> And behold, here they are, to whom I am betray'd. <hi>Whom is it you ſeek for, Soldiers,</hi> with your Lanthorns and Torches? Whom is it you look for? <hi>Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth? <hi>I am he.</hi> What gaze you for? I tell you, I am he.</p>
            <p>The Signal was before agreed upon, That whomſoever <hi>Judas</hi> kiſs'd, him they muſt ſeize; therefore the ſtrict Order before concluded of, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to them, muſt punctually be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, leſt a diſcovery ſhould be made, and they ſeize the wrong, and the King of the Jews make his eſcape. The Plot being laid thus cunningly and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily before-hand, they muſt not too raſhly nor unadviſedly proceed, but ſtood looking earneſtly till the Signal ſhould be given. <hi>Judas,</hi> thô the dark Night conceal me from thy Sight, yet here I am: <hi>The hour is now come,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110425:14"/>that the Son of Man muſt be betray'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of Sinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then <hi>Judas</hi> came and cry'd, <hi>Hail Maſter!</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judas</hi> betrays him.</note> 
               <hi>and kiſſed him, and ſtraight way</hi> (or forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with) <hi>they laid violent hands on him.</hi> What makes you come thus, <hi>with Swords and with Staves,</hi> Judas, as if I were <hi>a Thief and a Robber?</hi> And they began immediately to <hi>ſpit in his Face; and one of the Soldiers ſmote him on the Cheek with the Palm of his hand, and asked him, who ſtruck him.</hi> But <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſaid to <hi>Judas,</hi> take me, and lead me away, and thy own Salvation too. <hi>I have a Baptiſm to be Baptiz'd with, and O, how I long till it is accompliſht.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Peter</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours his Maſter's Reſcue.</note>But <hi>Peter,</hi> as ſoon as he ſaw what inhumane rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they offer'd to his Lord and Maſter, haſtily <hi>drew his Sword, and cut off one of the Ears of the High Prieſt's Servants. Then</hi> Jeſus <hi>rebuked</hi> Peter, <hi>and ſaid, put thy Sword up into the Sheath; He that uſeth the Sword, let him periſh by the Sword: The Cup that my Father giveth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110425:15"/>me, ſhall I not drink it?</hi> John 18. v. 8. 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thinkeſt thou not,</hi> Peter, <hi>that if I would reſiſt, I would pray to my Father, and he would preſently give me more than twelve Legions of Angels to reſcue me; but how then ſhall the Scriptures be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill'd? And it pleaſed the Lord to bruiſe him, and put him to Grief, when his Soul ſhall make and Offering for Sin, he ſhall ſee his Seed: he ſhall ſee of the Travel of his Soul, and be ſatisfied: By his knowledge ſhall my Righteous Servant juſtifie many, for he ſhall bear their Iniquities,</hi> Iſa. ch. 53. v. 10, 11.</p>
            <p>But ſtay, O <hi>Malchus!</hi> what,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Malchus</hi>'s Ear healed.</note> wilt thou ſtill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in this bloody Deed and wicked Proceedings? Wilt thou not hear the Voice of thy God in this Fray? Thou ſhedd'ſt but a drop of Blood from thy Ear, and thy Saviour Sweats, not only drops of Blood in his Agony, praying for thy Soul, but alſo his Heart bleeds for thee, and he takes immediately Compaſſion of thee, and <hi>ſtretch'd forth his hand and cur'd thy Ear?</hi> And could not this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of the Lord of Life toward thee work perfectly upon thee to endeavour
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110425:15"/>thy Phyſicians Reſcue? but ſtill wilt thou go on to drag and hale him before the Judge? Will not the immediate Touch of the Hand of God cure thy wounded Soul, as readily as thy woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Body? Will not this Miracle of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and Love of his to thee, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade thee, That he is <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Son of the Living God? Wilt thou remain ignorant ſtill of thy Saviour and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? How many of the Multitude that follow'd <hi>Chriſt</hi> would have thought themſelves happy to have been bleſt with ſuch a Touch? yea, that it might be but the <hi>Hem of his Garment.</hi> Well, if thou wilt ſtill proceed in perſecuting him, he will proceed in praying for thee, with the reſt of thy Confederates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter!</hi> Was this the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of thy Paſſion,<note place="margin">Chriſt <hi>repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> Peter.</note> juſt rous'd from ſleep, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to fight? When ſaw'ſt thou ſuch Weapons uſed in my School? Was ever any thing but Prayers and Tears my Defence? Haſt thou over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlept, and neglected thy God, and now fall immediately to fighting? Couldſt not <hi>thou</hi> and thy Brethren <hi>have watch'd and pray'd with thy Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110425:16"/>for one hour?</hi> eſpecially when wak'd and ſtirr'd up by thy Maſter, and when he had ſo lately told you the time was at hand in which he muſt be betray'd, and by one of thy Brother Diſciples. Shouldſt not thou rather have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to have watch'd the time of his coming, and diſſuaded him from his intended Wickedneſs? eſpecially when thou hadſt ſeen thy Saviour exceeding ſorrowful, even to Death. Was he earneſtly praying, and in his Agony ſweating drops of Blood, dropping up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Ground for thee? And couldſt not thou be watching for him? but ſit ſleeping upon the Ground with the reſt of thy Companions. Or if you had been ſo extremely ſleepy, could you not have took your turns one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? This, <hi>Peter,</hi> is great neglect of ſo good a Maſter. Was he ſtriving, and ſtruggling, ſweating, and praying to his Heavenly Father, for thy Soul, and couldſt not thou be watching of his Body? But he, being upon the Work of Salvation, excuſes thy Infirmity, from the Conſideration of thy frail hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature, that was not able to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo one ſingle hours watch. I know,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110425:16"/>
               <hi>Peter, thy Spirit is willing, but thy Fleſh is weak.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How ready and willing is the Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the World to accept of any drowſy inclinations, or endeavours of his Servants, in his Service, if their Hearts be but ſincere. The Diſciples ſlumber, yet Chriſt trims their Lamps. O infinite Love of the Son of God! to excuſe and ſave poor drowſy Sinners: For this Cauſe was he <hi>toucht with our infirmities,</hi> and took upon him our human Nature. This was the Cauſe of our Saviours interceding for us with his Father for our Lives. O infinite Love of the Son of God! <hi>that whilſt we were yet Sinners, Chriſt dy'd for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us follow him to the <hi>Judgment-Hall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Carry'd to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Hall to be arraign'd, but firſt to <hi>Anna</hi>'s Houſe.</note> and not, like <hi>Peter,</hi> ſtand at a diſtance from him, and at laſt deny him, but rather be a ſharer with him in his Death, and pray, with the Thief upon the Croſs, for Eternal Life.</p>
            <p>They carry him firſt before <hi>Annas</hi> the High-Prieſt, <hi>Caiphas</hi>'s Uncle, and in the way to his Houſe, to ſee what he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110425:17"/>could find againſt him. This was one of the Great Council, that <hi>conſulted how they might take Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth <hi>King of the Jews,</hi> and put him to Death. This was he, that deliver'd to <hi>Judas</hi> the thirty pieces of Silver out of the Treaſury, after they had all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon it; but when he was brought before him, and he ſaw the Witneſſes could not agree together upon their Examination, that they might have longer time to lay their Heads toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and more readily agree in their Accuſation, ſends them to his Nephew <hi>Caiphas,</hi> they being both <hi>High-Prieſts that year.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he comes before <hi>Caiphas,</hi> he Examines him, and finding they could not yet agree in their accuſing him, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than he ſhould want full Witneſſes againſt him, and for that let him go; he with the reſt of them that were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled together for the very purpoſe, all the High-Prieſts and Elders, and the Scribes, for many there were that did bear falſe Witneſs againſt him, but <hi>their Witneſſes agreed not</hi> yet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:110425:17"/>Now the Great Aſſembly being all met, as I ſaid before, to this very end and purpoſe, and conſulted and agreed thus farther of him: He hath of late raiſed <hi>Lazarus</hi> out of the Grave, after he had been ſour days dead, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſtink, and many of the <hi>Jews</hi> believe on him already, from the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles that he daily ſheweth amongſt them, and more eſpecially for this Miracle that he wrought even now, of raiſing <hi>Lazarus</hi> from the Dead; and it is not barely a Report, to make a noiſe for a while, but it is, as to Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact, a very great Truth and a Miracle, for ſome of us both heard him ſay at the Graves Mouth, <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus come forth,</hi> and he immediately, as ſoon as this Man had call'd thus to him, <hi>he that was dead came forth; bound hands and feet, with Grave-Cloaths a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, and a Napkin upon</hi> his Head; And this Man Jeſus <hi>commanded ſome that ſtood by to looſe him and let him go; and many of the Jews that were there believed on him</hi> and went away with <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Jeſus;</hi> but we came to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you, what we have <hi>both ſeen and heard,</hi> John 11.43.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:110425:18"/>
               <hi>Then the Chief Prieſts and Elders,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 11.47.</note> 
               <hi>with the Scribes and Phariſees further conſulted, and ſaid, What do we? for this Man doth many Miracles, and if we let him thus alone, all Men will believe on him and the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans <hi>will come and take away</hi> from us, both our Place and Nation. Caiphas <hi>ſaid unto them, ye know nothing at all, nor conſider that it is expedient for us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caiphas</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</note> 
               <hi>that one Man ſhould dye for the People, and that the Nation periſh not; and this he ſpake not of himſelf, but God order'd</hi> it ſo, that the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſhould come out of his own Mouth, and this being Recorded as his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doth ſtill remain, that out of his own Mouth himſelf ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd at laſt; And ſo from <hi>that day forward they took Counſel together to put him to Death.</hi> John 11.53.</p>
            <p>And when they ſaw that all their Machinations and Contrivances pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd nothing to the purpoſe, at laſt they hir'd two Soldiers, and gave <hi>them Money</hi> to come and ſwear againſt him in the High Prieſts Hall; And they with a loud and clamarous Voice ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110425:18"/>above the reſt, with open Mouth ſay, <hi>This Fellow ſaid, I am able to deſtroy the Temple of God, and to raiſe it again in three days.</hi> And ſo he were, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Truth; but he ſpake of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> That in three days time he ſhould raiſe it from the Grave; But theſe two Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows nor his Judges had not yet <hi>known the Scriptures, nor the power of God. Then ſaid the High Prieſt, Is it true what theſe two witneſs againſt thee? But</hi> Jeſus <hi>held his peace. Then ſaid the High Prieſt, I adjure thee by the Living God, to tell us whether thou art Chriſt the Son of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God?</hi> And <hi>Jeſus</hi> when it was put thus home to him, in theſe three great Truths, <hi>Art thou Chriſt, the Son of the Living</hi> God? Anſwered, <hi>I am. Then the High Prieſt rent his Cloaths, and ſaid, What need we any further witneſs againſt him? Ye have all heard now how he hath Blaſphemed; What think ye? And they all with one conſenting Voice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd him to be guilty of Death.</hi> Matth. 26.60, 6, 62, 63, 64. Mark 14.58. <hi>to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 64.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:110425:19"/>
               <hi>Then they began to ſpit upon him, and to buffet him, and ſtrike him with the Palms of their hands, and to revile</hi> him as a Peſtilent Fellow, and one that ſow'd Sedition and Rebellion amongſt them, and they blind-folded him, <hi>and ſmote him on the Face, and ſaid unto him, Propheſie now unto us (Chriſt!) who it was that ſtruck thee;</hi> And at laſt, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they could not agree together as to the putting of him to death, and to paſs Sentence upon him, for they all acquieſc'd in the juſt Merits of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; yet he muſt be firſt ſent to <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> their Chief Governor: But before we come to that, we muſt obſerve the Words of our Bleſſed <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> verify'd concerning <hi>Peter,</hi> one of the beloved Diſciples, who follow'd after his Maſter to the High Prieſt's Hall, to hear what they ſaid of him, and did with him.</p>
            <p>And happy are they, O <hi>Peter,</hi> that have once deny'd their Saviour that bought them, with Curſing and Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bitter Execrations, to find a door of Mercy ready open upon their Repentance, to receive them again, and immediately embrace them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:110425:19"/>And now <hi>Peter,</hi> what do I obſerve here? But thou that waſt the greateſt Votary to thy Maſter, and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeſt to follow him to his diſmal Trial, where were all kind of the moſt wicked Profligate Wretches, that could be pickt out amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> Scribes, and Phariſees, that were beſt and moſt notoriouſly qualify'd with Curſing and Swearing, with Reviling, Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and Perjury, ſuch that they had cull'd out on purpoſe, that were qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify'd and abounded with all manner of Cruelty and Filthineſs; amongſt theſe do I find thee, <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And had thy Soul, like <hi>Righteous Lot</hi>'s been troubled with the <hi>filthineſs of the Sodomites,</hi> as his was <hi>from day to day,</hi> thou hadſt not ſo ſoon, ſo falſly, and ſo frequently deny'd thy Maſter: From hence we may obſerve, what ſorce and power evil Company hath quickly upon a Righteous Perſon. Good <hi>Joſeph</hi> being but a while in <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi>'s Court, came preſently to that Mode of Honour to ſwear <hi>by the Life of Pharaoh. Abraham,</hi> the <hi>Father of the Faithful,</hi> and <hi>friend of God,</hi> twice deny'd <hi>Sarah</hi> to be his Wife: The
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110425:20"/>Famine being grievous in the Land, <hi>Abraham</hi> takes his Wife <hi>Sarah,</hi> and travels into <hi>Egypt, and it came to paſs, when he came near to enter into</hi> Egypt, <hi>that he ſaid unto</hi> Sarah <hi>his Wife, behold now, I know that thou art a fair Woman to look upon, therefore it ſhall come to paſs, that when the</hi> Egyptians <hi>ſhall ſee thee, they ſhall ſay, this is his Wife, and they ſhall kill me, and they ſhall ſave thee alive; ſay, I pray thee, thou art my Siſter.</hi> Gen. 12.10, 11, 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again</hi> Abimelech <hi>ſaid unto</hi> Abraham, <hi>What ſaweſt thou in me, that thou haſt done this thing? And</hi> Abraham <hi>ſaid, becauſe I thought ſurely the fear of God is not in this Place, and they will ſlay me for my Wifes ſake; and yet indeed ſhe is my Siſter, the Daughter of my Father, though not of my Mother, and ſhe became my Wife:</hi> And here <hi>Abraham,</hi> though he did deny his Wife at this time out of fear, and did wander from Place to Place, and Country to Country, yet he did not deny his God, neither could <hi>Abimelech</hi> tax him with that: For God had now made a Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the chiefeſt Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle in this Covenant, was, <hi>That</hi> Sarah
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110425:20"/>
               <hi>ſhould conceive and bear him a Son in his old Age, and ſhould call his Name</hi> Iſaac; And, ſaid God, <hi>I will continue my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to him, ſo that in thy Seed,</hi> by <hi>Sarah</hi> thy Wife, <hi>ſhall all the Nations of the World be bleſſed: And it ſhall be for number as the Stars of the Heaven, and as the Sands on the Sea-ſhoar; yea, Kings and Princes ſhall come out of thy Loyns, and I will give thee the Land of</hi> Canaan <hi>for an Everlaſting Poſſeſſion to dwell in: And I will be thy God, and the God of thy Seed for ever.</hi> Neither did <hi>Abraham</hi> deny his Son <hi>Iſaac</hi> to God, when he call'd for him as a trial of his Faith: But all theſe Promiſes and Covenants concentrating together, and terminating in <hi>Sarah</hi>'s Womb, made <hi>Abraham</hi> take ſuch care of her; for it was not in <hi>Iſhmael, but in</hi> Iſaac <hi>ſhall thy Seed be called,</hi> Gen. 17. and that <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth</hi> King of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould proceed out of his Loyns.</p>
            <p>But now, <hi>Peter,</hi> this is no excuſe for thee; for <hi>Abraham,</hi> in ſaying, <hi>ſhe was his Siſter,</hi> did not deny her to be his Wife; moreover in all Ages, and all times, eſpecially in the times and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Plague, Famine, or Sword, it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110425:21"/>hath been allow'd to ſome to fly, and either to equivocate or excuſe the Queſtion, when propos'd by implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Enemies; Our Saviour himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Diſciples were fully prepar'd for Perſecution, and found in themſelves they were not able to ſtand the hard and ſevere, or Fiery, Trials they might be put upon, and ſo his Name, or his great Cauſe, might ſuffer by it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to avoid ſuch, bid them, <hi>If they perſecuted them in one City,</hi> for my Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake, and the Goſpel's ſake, to <hi>fly into another;</hi> but this was no denying him, and the Church hath always allow'd it, in two Caſes eſpecially, to fly and avoid Perſecution; The one, if the Church was in its infancy, and not come to full ſtrength,<note place="margin">For this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon fled <hi>Greg.</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Neocaeſaria,</hi> when he ſaw the Decian Perſecution grow very hot. Pr. Chr. Ch. <hi>7.</hi> part <hi>2.</hi> N. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> then it might be lawful for the Miniſters or Diſciples of Chriſt to flee Perſecution, to the intent the Goſpel might be preſerv'd, leſt ſmiting the Shepherd the Sheep ſhould be ſcatter'd; And the other is, in Caſe, as I mention'd before, they find themſelves not yet ſtrong enough,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110425:21"/>or courageous enough for Perſecution, and ſo the Glory of God, and the Name of our great Maſter, and the Honour of the Church of Chriſt, might come to be diſhonour'd: This as to the firſt.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> to avoid Perſecution, was <hi>let down the Wall in a Basket, when the Governor of</hi> Damaſcus <hi>ſought his Life;</hi> and thus we find the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhunn'd the Storm, becauſe they were the Inſtruments immediately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted by Chriſt to propagate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the Goſpel to the World: And thus did Primitive Saints and Martyrs who <hi>wonder'd about in Deſarts and Mountains, and in Dens and Caves of the Earth,</hi> and ſo have equally avoided Raſhneſs and Cowardlineſs.</p>
            <p>The ſecond only gain'd a little reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit for the preſent, that they might ſuffer with the greater advantage after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, thus did <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> from the Command of God by an Angel, <hi>flee with their Child,</hi> the Ever-Bleſſed Jeſu <hi>into Egypt</hi> for fear of <hi>Herod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, <hi>Peter,</hi> 'twas quite contrary with you, you was not call'd to ſuffer, neither to the High-Prieſts Hall; yet
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110425:22"/>thou voluntarily deny'dſt thy Maſter, thy Saviour, and thy Redeemer, who oft had told you what you muſt expect, and that the <hi>time would come, that he muſt be betrayed into the hands of Sinners;</hi> and but the very night before told you, that you <hi>all would be offended becauſe of him, and that the time would come, and was now at hand, that you all would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him,</hi> in the time of his Dereliction, and he be left alone: And didſt not thou thy ſelf ſay? This was <hi>a hard ſaying, and who could bear it?</hi> and ſaid'ſt, <hi>thou wouldſt not be offended becauſe of him, and if all forſook him, yet wouldſt not thou;</hi> True, thou didſt not ſo much forſake him, as deny him, which was worſe.</p>
            <p>And, indeed, <hi>Peter,</hi> I muſt follow thee, as thou didſt thy Maſter, the Ever-Bleſſed and Eternal Jeſu, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the World, to the High-Prieſts Hall; And Pardon me, <hi>Peter,</hi> if I exactly obſerve every behaviour of thine there. It is not out of any ill to thee, <hi>Peter,</hi> for I very well know the love and value thy Maſter hath for thee, but that I may delineate thee to the Life, as fully and as well as I am
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110425:22"/>able, in this little <hi>Enchiridion,</hi> what Sorrows, what Sufferings, what Stripes, what Indignities, what Reproaches, what Revilings, what Dereliction, what Abnegations, what Wounds, what Agony, and what Unexpreſſable Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, what Extenſive, Convulſive, Diſtorſive, Lingring, and Cruciating Death, thy Lord and Maſter, but our Chriſt, our Saviour, our Redeemer, our Meſſias, and our bleſſed <hi>Jeſu,</hi> our Advocate not only now in Heaven, <hi>where he is exalted above all Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Powers, Thrones and Dominions;</hi> but while he was here on Earth, the Immaculate Lamb, the moſt beloved Son of God, beloved of the Father from all Eternity, before ever the World was, and <hi>Lamb of God which taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Sins of the whole World;</hi> he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered and endured here on Earth for us, which made him bitterly complain, and cry out; <hi>Behold, and ſee, all ye that paſs by, if there were ever any Sorrow like to my Sorrow, any Wounds and Torments like mine, which I have receiv'd in the Houſe of my friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:110425:23"/>Canſt thou receive, ſuffer, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, all this for our Sins, and ſtill call us friends? Canſt thou, O Holy <hi>Jeſu,</hi> ſtill cry, call, ſuffer, bleed, and dye for us, and yet pray for us, and ſtill be an Advocate for us, and a compleat Redeemer. O infinite! O unlimited! O unbounded! O inconceiveable! O inexpreſſible! O incomprehenſible Love of God to us, <hi>that ſo loved the World, than he gave his only begotten Son</hi> to Death for us, for us Sinners, wicked Sinners, apoſtatizing Sinners, even <hi>dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins;</hi> and all this, <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> thou art not ignorant of.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Peter,</hi> more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to thy ſelf.<note place="margin">The Firſt Denial of <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </note> And, as <hi>Peter</hi> was beneath in the Palace, there cometh one of the <hi>Maids of the High Prieſt,</hi> and when ſhe ſaw <hi>Peter,</hi> warming of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf amongſt the Croud, <hi>ſhe looked ſteadfaſtly upon him,</hi> and ſaid in deriſion, <hi>Thou alſo waſt with Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>but he denied, ſaying, I know not, neither do I underſtand what thou ſayeſt: And he went out into the Porch,</hi> as fearing they might ſeize on him, tho' but the Night before he had ſaid, <hi>Tho' all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110425:23"/>thee, yet will not I:</hi> But he ſtill lingers and ſtays, not that he intended to ſuffer and dye with his Maſter, as he had promiſed, but only had a mind to ſee what would become of his Maſter, and to hear what they did ſay to him, for now was the time that our Saviour told him, The Devil will tempt you, <hi>Peter; Satan hath a mind to winnow thee as Wheat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but I have prayed for thee;</hi> and well were it for thee, <hi>(Peter)</hi> that whatever thy Maſter endur'd for thee in his Sacred Body, yet he had ſecur'd thy Soul: <hi>I have prayed for thee, thy Faith fail thee not:</hi> And as he was ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Porch, the <hi>Cock crew the firſt time;</hi> but as yet, neither the Time, nor the Scripture, was fulfilled, nor did <hi>Peter</hi> take any notice of it, <hi>Mark</hi> 14.68.</p>
            <p>And while he was yet in the Porch,<note place="margin">The Second.</note> another <hi>Maid ſaw him, and ſaid unto them that were likewiſe with her, This very fellow</hi> (pointing to him) <hi>was alſo with Jeſus of Galilee; and when he had heard what ſhe ſaid, he flatly denied with an Oath, I know not the man,</hi> Matth. 26.71, 72.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:110425:24"/>How now, <hi>Peter,</hi> now I ſee the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is tempting thee, indeed: Haſt thou ſo much forgot thy ſelf, and thy Duty to ſo good and ſo great a Maſter? Are all his Miracles forgot by thee? Are all his Leſſons, Inſtructions, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons or Sayings, forgot by thee? Are his very laſt and dying Words too forgot by thee? And are thy own Promiſes and Engagements to thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting and dying Saviour, forgot by thee? This is a great Crime indeed, <hi>Peter,</hi> and in all Ages and Times hath been accounted moſt abominable, and unworthy, not to fulfil the Requeſt of our dying Friends and Relations; and alſo, not to perform our Promiſes to their dying Perſon, and laſt Gaſp; and eſpecially for thee, <hi>Peter,</hi> who hadſt ſo dear and tender a Lord and Maſter that had took ſuch pains with thee, and care of thee, whoſe Words one would have thought could never have been forgot by thee, more eſpecially not ſo ſoon, and at this very inſtant, when thou waſt ſo near, as to hear how thy Heavenly Maſter, was confronted and abuſed, and moſt wrong fully impeach'd, and moſt falſely accus'd, yet not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſcentiate
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:110425:24"/>the words of thy Maſter, but when thou waſt ſo peremptorily charg'd, thou ſo flatly denied. Well, <hi>Peter,</hi> thou wilt pay for this at laſt: It's well thou haſt a friend in Court.</p>
            <p>Then came <hi>one of the Servants of the High Prieſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Third.</note> 
               <hi>being his Kinſman, and whoſe Ear</hi> Peter <hi>had out off,</hi> charges him home, and ſays, <hi>Did not I ſee thee in the Garden with him?</hi> And doſt not thou very well know, I have a juſt Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel againſt thee? And this is a fit place for it, for cutting off my Ear, when I laid hands of your Maſter in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. Look here, and behold the mark I ſtill bear of my Ear for thee, and if it were not that my Kinſman was ſo buſie with thy Maſter, and I do not know how ſoon I may be called, and therefore am unwilling to create ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fray and Diſturbance, otherwiſe I would make thee an Example, and make you know, you was thee, I have no ſo quickly forgot you, nor your Ear-mark neither, <hi>John</hi> 18.26. And moreover, if you ſhould deny, and lye never ſo much, if there were no more
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:110425:25"/>in it but your Speech, <hi>your very Speech it ſelf is enough to betray you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then began</hi> Peter, <hi>when he had heard all this, to Curſe and to Swear with all the Execrations imaginable,</hi> and poſitive Denials. I never ſaw before this time the Man, <hi>neither do I know him, and immediately the Cock crew,</hi> Matth. 26.74. <hi>And the Lord turned back, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſteadfaſtly on</hi> Peter; <hi>and</hi> Peter <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that, remembred the Words of his Maſter, how he had ſaid unto him, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Cock crow twice, thou ſhalt deny me thrice, and he went out, and wept bitterly,</hi> Luk 22.61, 62.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Peter,</hi> art thou in the <hi>Gaul of Bitterneſs,</hi> and in the <hi>Bond of Iniquity;</hi> now thou know'ſt not where to hide thy head, now the very <hi>Arrows of the Almighty, pierce the very Soul</hi> of thee, now thou ſeeſt thou art fallen; <hi>Let him that ſtandeth</hi> take precaution by thy Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>leſt he fall</hi> in the ſame manner thou haſt done.</p>
            <p>What! deny thy Maſter, <hi>Peter?</hi> thy Saviour, and thy Redeemer? And what! with ſuch abominable Oaths, and poſitive Denials? This would make the very <hi>dumb Aſs to open his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:110425:25"/>Mouth,</hi> and upbraid thy unparalell'd unkindneſs. Thou, alone, <hi>Peter,</hi> to be the Man to deny thy Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who had the moſt reaſon of any of the Diſciples to have own'd him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe preſent with him, and hearing the Ignominy and notorious Slanders that they impudently ſpake againſt him, thy own Conſcience bearing thee Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>O, how, with <hi>Cain,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Peter</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining and praying for himſelf.</note> am I branded with my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy! <hi>My Sins are greater than I am able to bear.</hi> O, that ſome one would even ſlay me. What! deny my Maſter! My Lord and Maſter! my God! my Saviour and my Redeemer! and my ever bleſſed <hi>Jeſus!</hi> What! and three times! and with Curſing and Swearing too, that I did not know thee! O, ſweet Jeſu! not thee! what, not know thee! O, heavenly Jeſu! that brought me up from the beginning! that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted me to the Faith! that made me one of thy Diſciples, and not the leaſt neither! one that thou more remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly took'dſt notice of, and care for, and foretold me of this very preſent hour,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110425:26"/>of <hi>Satan</hi>'s Tempting me, and pray'd earneſtly for me to be deliver'd from this fatal hour.</p>
            <p>O bleſſed Jeſu! well was it, that thou didſt pray for me, or elſe I had been eternally loſt. How can I but weep, and <hi>weep bitterly</hi> for this heinous and never-to-be-forgotten Sin? <hi>O, wretched man that I am! who ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me?</hi> Was not my firſt Sin great enough in the Garden? to ſleep when thou wert in thy Agony, and bid me watch; but muſt I commit a greater now? A Sin none ever did commit, nor ever can again, as to the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, Time, and Place: Lord, help me to weep, and to weep more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly. O, Lord! that I could waſh away my Sins, with my Tears, that are, of ſo deep a dye.</p>
            <p>O, bleſſed Jeſu! to make my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſtronger, I will back again to the Garden of <hi>Gethſemane,</hi> to bewail my firſt Sin; that was the place I was firſt neglective of my God: And there alſo I will bewail the ſecond too. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that is the fitteſt place, O my Soul! There was the place my dear Lord and Saviour, in his great Conflict, pray'd
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110425:26"/>and wept, and made <hi>ſtrong Supplications to his God, with Sighs and Groans that were unutterable;</hi> there he <hi>fell with his Face to the Ground, and humbled himſelf even unto Death,</hi> there is the place, he ſweat drops of Blood in, mixt with his Tears, for me; thither will I run, and there will I proſtrate my ſelf on the Ground in the very ſame place, and as I ſaid before, to make my Laver ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to waſh my polluted Crimſon-dyed Soul, I will mix the Blood and Tears of my dear Lord and Saviour, that are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Ground, with my own Hearts blood and Tears.</p>
            <p>O, ſweet Jeſu! I remember now very well thy laſt Words and thy laſt Prayers; and with theſe unparalell'd Ingredients I find here my poor ſinking Soul begins to revive,<note place="margin">The Tears and Drops of Sweat and Blood that fell upon the Ground from our Saviour in his Agony.</note> and my Faith in thee, dear Jeſu, ſprings again amain; and I ſee the Door of Mercy open to me, as well as to <hi>Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> to us that have ſinned much; thou haſt heard our Prayers, and haſt ſeen and botled up our Tears, and <hi>haſt forgiven much. But I have
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110425:27"/>pray'd for thee,</hi> Peter, <hi>thy Faith fail thee not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O, happy was it for thee, <hi>Peter,</hi> when thou waſt ſo deſperately woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to have thy Phyſician ſo near with <hi>the Balm of</hi> Gilead, like the <hi>good Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan, to pour Oyl and Wine into thy Wounds,</hi> to ſupple and cleanſe them, and carefully bind them up for healing. If thy Saviour had paſſed by thee, and had not look'd upon thee, thy Wounds had putrifi'd and gangrean'd, and thou hadſt been loſt for ever. If Chriſt himſelf had not took notice of thee, and heal'd thy wounds, all others had paſs'd by thee, Scribe and Phariſee, Jew and Gentile, ſome on the Right hand, and ſome on the Left, and no Man had taken Pity of thee. Happy are they that lye in the way Chriſt doth walk, yea, even at the Pool of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> they are ſure to be heard by Chriſt, the Phyſician of Souls; they ſhall either be ſure of his immediate help, or elſe of his Angels, that are miniſtring Spirits ſent from him.</p>
            <p>O! that I might as effectually find the Prayers of my dear Jeſu for me, <hi>Peter,</hi> in the full Pardon of my Sins,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:110425:27"/>now enthron'd in Heaven, as thou found'ſt him for thine on Earth. To <hi>open blind Eyes,</hi> and to take off Scales of Ignorance with St. <hi>Paul: Are not the Waters of</hi> Siloam <hi>to waſh in better than</hi> Abana <hi>and</hi> Pharpar, <hi>and all the Rivers of</hi> Damaſcus?</p>
            <p>But now to return back to <hi>Caiphas</hi> and his Confederates and Council, they being made up of the Chief-Prieſts, Elders, Scribes, and Phariſees, they unanimouſly agree, according to their Arbitrary Law, to condemn Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth;</hi> but they had <hi>no Power to put him to Death,</hi> but after they had u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the Villany to him they could, as ſpitting upon him, buffetting him, ſtriking of him on the Face with the Palms of their Hands, and blindfold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him, and asking, <hi>who it was that ſmote him,</hi> and with all the Reviling ill Language they were capable of, they very early the next Morning ſent him bound to <hi>Pilate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, when <hi>Judas</hi> found, that <hi>Caiphas</hi> had condemn'd him, and ſent him to <hi>Pilate,</hi> he begins to <hi>repent of what he had done, and carries back the Thirty Pieces of Silver</hi> to the High-Prieſts,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110425:28"/>
               <hi>Annas</hi> and <hi>Caiphas:</hi> But more of that in the concluſion of his notorious Wickedneſs in betraying his Maſter. But now, as to the manner and behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of <hi>Judas,</hi> and the Report abroad.</p>
            <p>What! What! What news is this I hear?<note place="margin">A devout Soul amazed at the report of <hi>Judas</hi>'s be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying his Maſter.</note> My bleſſed Lord and Redeemer betraid! <hi>Betraid by a kiſs!</hi> and by one of his own Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, at the time of his Prayers, and in the place of his greateſt Retirements, in the dark Night, where none could hear him or ſee him, but his God, his Heavenly Father; and betray'd at this time by <hi>Judas,</hi> while he was praying. O, Wonder and Amazement! While he was praying for his Diſciples! O, how happy would my Soul have been, to have heard but on Whiſper from thy Mouth, dear Saviour, to thy God, in my behalf, for my poor Soul. Thus was it with thee at this time; Praying and Pleading with thy Heavenly Father for the Salvation of Mankind, and more eſpecially for his Diſciples, to whom he was to commit the care of his poor ſcatter'd and diſtreſſed Flock, and for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:110425:28"/>thee, <hi>Judas,</hi> he was praying with <hi>ſtrong Prayers, Cries and Tears,</hi> and the <hi>more earneſtly</hi> at this time of thy coming was he labouring and interced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with his Father, with Sighs and Groans, and in a very great Agony of Soul and Body, even to the extorting and drawing out <hi>great drops of Blood,</hi> the fell to the Ground. And how couldſt thou come thus, <hi>Judas,</hi> with Tapers and Lights, as if <hi>thou wert</hi> (with the bleſſed Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi>) <hi>Sick of Love,</hi> as if no time or place could retain thee, or keep thee longer from thy beloved, nor no danger could affright thee from the Terrors of the dark and gloomy Night, but find him thou art re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved of, &amp; no ſooner hadſt thou found him, but how paſſionately, one would think, thou runn'ſt to him, and hang'ſt about his Neck, and kiſſeſt him, as if it expreſt the greateſt Paſſion and Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency of thy Soul, with the moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Compleatment of thy Longings and Deſires, to find out thy moſt endeared Friend; as if thou hadſt come to him with the greateſt Embaſſy or News, that God or Angels could reveal to thee, or employ thee in; or, as if thou hadſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:110425:29"/>privately over-heard the dreadful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy of the High-Prieſts and Elders, Governour, Soldiers, and <hi>Herod,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy Lord and Maſter's precious Life; and as if this had been the only Minute and Time, in this dark and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Night, to make his Eſcape in; and thou thy ſelf, with thy Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers and Lights,<note place="margin">Dark Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorns.</note> hadſt come ſecretly to conduct him ſecurely through By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways and untrodden Paths, that he might go conceal'd from theſe notorious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators; which, if this very Minute was not improv'd to this Advantage, thy Lord was unavoidably taken, to the Loſs of his moſt precious Life, by theſe moſt accurſed Miſcreants and Blood-Hounds of Hell.</p>
            <p>This, <hi>Judas,</hi> had been Love indeed, and could Men or Angels, that had no foreknowledge of any deſign, have judg'd it otherwiſe? And greater Love than this could not poſſibly have been ſhewn, thus privately and reſolvedly to have ventur'd thy own Life for thy Maſter's. Or, <hi>Judas,</hi> it's a wonder, that, before thy foul and polluted Mouth came to his ſacred Lips, thou
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:110425:29"/>couldſt not diſcern the Tears and Drops of Blood upon his Heavenly Face; or when thou hadſt once kiſs'd him, through ſuddain eagerneſs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcerning, yet the moiſture of an unuſual Kiſs ſhould have made thee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately have look'd upon his diſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Agonious Face, and there preſently have ſeen written in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of Blood,<note place="margin">Jeſus oft' kiſſed his Diſciples.</note> the intent of thy abominable ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, and wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and that it was not unknown or unlook'd for, and expected by thy Lord and Maſter, who the very Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before had ſaid, at the very time <hi>of eating the Paſſover</hi> together with his Diſciples, <hi>I ſhall be betray'd this nigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> into the hands of the moſt wicked <hi>Jews,</hi> and it ſhall be done too by the hands of <hi>one of my own Diſciples, and he that dippeth his hand with me in the Diſh, the ſame is he that ſhall betray me.</hi> And haſt thou quite forgot, <hi>Judas,</hi> thou anſwer'd and ſaid, <hi>Is it I?</hi> Or, hadſt thou quite forgot thy Maſter had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready told thee, He knew the very thoughts of thy Heart, and of the reſt of thy Brethren, and had pray'd for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:110425:30"/>you, that <hi>the very thoughts of your Hearts, if poſſible, might be forgiven you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou, <hi>Judas,</hi> hadſt oft ſeen many Miracles done by thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,<note place="margin">The Earth open'd and ſwallow'd them up.</note> and waſt not thou afraid at this time, he might have wrought one, more upon thee, as upon <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> for <hi>offering ſtrange Fire unto the Lord,</hi> and thou at this time offering ſtrange Friendſhip; but will nothing of all this do, nor work upon thee to deter thee from thy Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Enterprize, and to alter thy wicked Intention?</p>
            <p>But art thou reſolv'd to give this betraying Kiſs, and to go on with thy former Mercenary unparalell'd Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and to ſtifle all Reflects, Retorts, or Reminiſcenciated Acts of Conſcience, and to cry, All <hi>Hail, Maſter,</hi> and give <hi>the Kiſs;</hi> And after this Kiſs of thine, <hi>Judas,</hi> canſt thou be looking upon, and be abetting, aiding, and aſſiſting theſe Vile Wretches, Officers, and Soldiers, in all their rage and violency, with their rude Hands, thus to drag thy Saviour, and pull him along, and with their Swords and Staves in their Hands,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:110425:30"/>to force him, and hale him on, and with their Lanthorns and Torches, the better to direct their blows upon thy Maſter. I ſay, <hi>Judas,</hi> couldſt thou ſee all this, and ſtill perſiſt in unrelen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and obdurate Impiety and Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence?</p>
            <p>Saith our Dear Saviour; <hi>Judas, are you come out, as againſt a Thief and a Robber, with Swords and with Staves to take me? I was daily with you in the Temple teaching, and you took me not, but the Scriptures muſt be fulfill'd, they all forſook him and fled,</hi> Mark 14.48, 49, 50.</p>
            <p>But thou, <hi>Judas, hear, thou deef,</hi> and <hi>look, thou blind,</hi> as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith; Will nothing of all this bring any thing to thy remembrance, nor to behold any thing in my innocent Face? <hi>Who is blind but my Servant, or deaf as the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger I ſent?</hi> Who is blind as he that is perfect in all this wickedneſs, and blind as the Lord's Servant? Seeing many things, but thou obſerveſt not: Opening the Ear, but thou heareſt not. The Lord is well pleas'd for his Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſs ſake; It becometh thus to be done, <hi>that all Scriptures might be fulfill'd.</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:110425:31"/>And canſt thou, <hi>Judas,</hi> be ignorant of them? Or, haſt thou blinded thy Eyes thus? And hardned thy Heart? And wholly ſold thy ſelf to the Devil, to work out and accompliſh this wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and cruelty, to thy Maſter, with thy Kiſs? <hi>Whomſoever I ſhall kiſs, the ſame is he, hold him faſt,</hi> Matth. 26.48.</p>
            <p>Now when <hi>Caiphas,</hi> and his Crew, had Examin'd Jeſus, and had all with one conſent unanimouſly voted his Death, yet it was beyond the Verge of their power to put into execution their deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd Sentence, but bound him, and ſent him away Malefactor-like to <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>When morning was come, all the Chief-Prieſts and Elders of the People take Counſel againſt Jeſus to put him to death, and when they had bound him, they led him away to</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>their Chief Governor. Then</hi> Judas <hi>which had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd him, when he ſaw how they had us'd him,</hi> and that he, that he had private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agreed with the betray him to, had proceeded further in his Malice and Rage to his Maſter, than was agreed upon at firſt, and had Condemn'd him
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:110425:31"/>to Death, and was now carrying him from one Court and Council to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and at this preſent time was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him to <hi>Pilate,</hi> and ſaw now it would be made a publick Buſineſs, of which he had a promiſe, it ſhould be only private, and that he muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitably be known to be the Man, and <hi>Vengeance then would not ſuffer him to live,</hi> nor yet ſhould he know where to hide his Head, when it was once come to be known amongſt all the reſt of the Diſciples, therefore he began to repent him, (as he thought, in time) and reſolv'd upon this courſe, to carry the Money back again to the High-Prieſts, and let them know, he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd falſe things againſt his Maſter, which were in no manner true, and therefore had brought them their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney again in full tale, and in the very ſame Bag, and threw it down upon the Treaſury-Table in the Temple, where before he had receiv'd it, and told them plainly, <hi>he repented, and had ſinn'd in betraying Innocent Blood,</hi> concluding in himſelf, this was the only Politick way left to ſave himſelf, and bring his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter off again, that he had ſo falſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:110425:32"/>But they took no notice of any thing that he ſaid to them, they had already made uſe of him as a Property to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth</hi> to them, that they had of along time-paſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to apprehend; and as for <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> in what he had done, whether well or ill to himſelf, what car'd they, he had done well for them, let him go and be hang'd, if he will, what do we care, ſay they, we will proceed with our ſport.</p>
            <p>And when he ſaw, that all that was ſaid and done, would prevail nothing upon the <hi>Jews,</hi> he goes out and lays vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent hands upon himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then</hi> Judas <hi>which had betray'd him, when he ſaw that they had condemn'd him, repented himſelf, and brought again the thirty pieces of Silver to the High-Prieſts and Elders, ſaying, I have ſinned in that I have betray'd the Innocent Blood, and they ſaid, What is that to us? ſee thou to that, and he caſt down the pieces of Silver in the Temple, and went out and hang'd himſelf.</hi> Matth. 25.5.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:110425:32"/>AND now, O moſt Holy Jeſu, let this Bleſſed Spirit further aſſiſt me in this great Work, to preſent thee, Dear Lord, to the Life, to my Devout Soul, that it may the more perfectly ſee thee in all thy Agony Paſſion, Death, Burial, Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion; and to admire thee, and adore thee, moſt Bleſſed Lord and Saviour, in the greateſt humiliation, and adoration, a poor Creature is able to do, as thou art daily interceding for me at the Throne of Heaven: And this I beg upon the bended Knees of my Soul, in thy own Name, and for thy own ſake, who art my Lord and Saviour, and Ever-Bleſſed Redeemer and Advocate. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now to proceed on with this wicked Tragedy of the <hi>Jews.</hi> After <hi>Judas</hi> had Hang'd himſelf, the Chief-Prieſts took the Silver-pieces, and ſaid, <hi>It is not lawful to put them into the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury becauſe it is the price of Blood; And they conſulted together, and bought the Potters Field to bury Strangers in, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Field is call'd the Field of Blood
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:110425:33"/>to this day. Then was fulfill'd that which was ſpoken by <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſaying, And they took the Thirty pieces of Silver, the price of him that was valued, whom they of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did value, and gave them for the Potters Field, as the Lord appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Jeſus <hi>carried before</hi> Pilate.</note> 
               <hi>But the High Prieſts took Jeſus, and bound him, and ſent him away very early</hi> (it being a work of darkneſs,) <hi>to Pilate,</hi> and they themſelves came after to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him. <hi>Pilate,</hi> entring the Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Seat, ask'd them, <hi>What Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they did bring againſt this Man,</hi> they anſwer and ſay in in general, <hi>If he were not a Malefactor, we would not have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd him up to you; Pilate</hi> being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to meddle in this Affair, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it was for envy they accus'd him, and not any thing of a juſt Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; <hi>Pilate</hi> ask'd them, Why they did not proceed againſt him, and <hi>judge him according to their Law,</hi> and not to trouble him? The <hi>Jews</hi> ſaid unto him, <hi>It is not lawful for us to put any Man to death, that the ſaying of Jeſus might be fulfill'd, which be ſpake, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:110425:33"/>what Death he ſhould dye,</hi> as he himſelf had propheſi'd of himſelf; <hi>And they ſhall deliver him to the Gentiles to mock, and to ſcourge, and to crucifie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then <hi>Pilate</hi> enter'd the Judgment-Hall, and when he ſaw no body come againſt him, calls to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, <hi>Art thou the King of the Jews?</hi> Thinking happily he might trap <hi>Jeſus</hi> in his words, but <hi>Jeſus</hi> as cautiouſly ask'd him another Queſtion; <hi>Haſt thou ſaid this thing of thy ſelf, or did others tell it thee of my?</hi> Pilate <hi>anſwer'd him, Am I a Jew? Thy own Nation, and the Chief Prieſts, have deliver'd thee to me, What haſt thou done? For as yet none can teſtifie any thing againſt him,</hi> for they had not as yet their pretended Fact ready, whereby to accuſe him; moreover, they found <hi>Pilate</hi> to be very ſtrict in his Examination, and very unwilling to be both Accuſer and Judge, and made them not willing to anſwer to any particulars, till they had drawn up full Proof againſt him, ſeeing a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Charge had no Influence upon <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late: Jeſus ſaid unto</hi> Pilate, <hi>my Kingdom is not of the World:</hi> Pilate <hi>therefore ſaid
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:110425:34"/>unto him, Art thou a King then? Jeſus anſwered, Thou ſayeſt that I am a King: For this Cauſe was I born, and for this Cauſe came I into the World, that I ſhould bear witneſs to the Truth: What is the Truth?</hi> ſaith <hi>Pilate:</hi> Jeſus anſwered, <hi>Every one that is of the Truth, heareth my Voice.</hi> Pilate <hi>then goes out to the Jews, and tells them,</hi> If <hi>they</hi> had nothing elſe to ſay againſt <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> he muſt, and will, diſcharge him; for <hi>be,</hi> for his part, <hi>found no fault in him at all,</hi> John 18.29. to 38.</p>
            <p>Then when they heard this, rather than he ſhould be diſcharg'd, the whole Multitude ran in with open Mouth, and began to accuſe him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, If we muſt come to Particulars, we are prepared. We found this Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>teaching Sedition and Rebellion,</hi> and endeavouring to pervert the Nation from <hi>paying Tribute to</hi> Caeſar, and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That himſelf is <hi>Chriſt, a King;</hi> ſaith <hi>Pilate,</hi> I have heard of this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and I will hear no more of it: I muſt diſcharge him, if this is all you have to ſay; for I tell you, <hi>I can find no fault in</hi> the Man: Then they were
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:110425:34"/>the more fierce againſt him, but all to no purpoſe, ſaying, <hi>He ſtirreth up the People, Teaching throughout</hi> Jury, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning from</hi> Galilee, <hi>to this place. Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> being now quite wearied out with this Nonſenſe, and hearing he was a Galilean, knew that he belong'd to <hi>Herod</hi>'s Juriſdiction, and turns him over to him, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.8 whom he knew to be at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> at that time,<note place="margin">Jeſus carried before <hi>Herod</hi>
               </note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſends Jeſus to him, who had been deſirous <hi>of a long ſeaſon to ſee him, becauſe he had heard many things of him; and hoped to ſee ſome of his Miracles done by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then <hi>Herod</hi> begins to Interrogate Jeſus, and finding he could get nothing from him, nor no Miracles to be done by him, and being moſt vehemently accuſed by the Chief Prieſts and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſaying all manner of Evil againſt him, that the ſubtilty of Men or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils could invent, for they diſtruſted to have any good done by <hi>Pilate,</hi> and therefore concluded, this was the laſt Stake they had to play, and thereupon reſolv'd to make the beſt of it. They
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:110425:35"/>ſaid that He pretended to be a King, and had forbid them to pay Tribute to any Earthly Monarch, and that he did frequently ſow Sedition amongſt the People; and moreover ſaid, <hi>He could deſtroy the Temple and build it again in three days:</hi> But he anſwered nothing to all this. Moreover, <hi>Herod</hi> was informed, they had been before <hi>Annas</hi> and <hi>Caiphas,</hi> and that their Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes could not agree together, and that <hi>Pilate</hi> could find no juſt Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Death againſt him, and, upon that account, had ſent him to him, which he took very kindly from <hi>Pilate,</hi> and upon this occaſion, they <hi>Two were made friends,</hi> which before had been at Variance and Enmity for a great while.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, <hi>Herod</hi> calls a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of his Mighty Men, and they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate the Matter amongſt themſelves, but yet could find no cauſe of Death in him, more than the violency of the People, ſo that <hi>Herod</hi> was neither wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to releaſe him, nor yet to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn him; but He and his Nobles make ſport with him awhile, ſet him at
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:110425:35"/>nought, <hi>mock'd him, and arrayed him in a Purple Robe,</hi> (others, <hi>a White Robe</hi>) out of deriſion to his Regal Power, and on purpoſe to render him more the peoples Scorn, and the more to enflame their mercileſs Cruelty, and thus return him back again to <hi>Pilate</hi> with Thanks, and a great Compliment for the grand favour he had done him, in ſending this Malefactor the <hi>King of the Jews</hi> to him. I have Rob'd him, and given him what Ignominy and Deſpite I thought convenient, but as for his Death, or to condemn him, belongs not to my Province, but more immediately to you, under <hi>Tiberius Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi>'s Government.</p>
            <p>And thus our Dear Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, the Lord of Life and Glory, is carried firſt to <hi>Annas,</hi> then to <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas,</hi> then to <hi>Pilate,</hi> afterwards to <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> and now back to <hi>Pilate</hi> again, toſs'd and tumbled up and down, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted no where to reſt, but poſted and hurried from one Court, Council, and Judgment-Seat, to another, and none could yet determine the Matter, but blind-folded, ſpit upon, and ſtruck
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:110425:36"/>in one Court, bound, mock'd, ſet at nought, and array'd in another; thump'd and revil'd in another; and ſcourg'd and buffeted almoſt in all, but yet not acquitted or diſcharg'd in any. Well might he bitterly complain; <hi>Foxes, have holes, and the Birds of the Air have Neſts, but the Son of Man hath not where to lay his Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now a ſecond time is our dear Jeſus brought before <hi>Pilate</hi> from <hi>Herod</hi>'s Court;<note place="margin">Jeſus carried before <hi>Pilate</hi> a ſecond time.</note> 
               <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> being now much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd at the Clamour abroad, that was made againſt <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth,</hi> by the moſt rude and common people, that run more by Tumult and Cry, than Reaſon and Judgment, and it appearing all along to be perfect, unheady, inconſiderate malice, <hi>Pilate</hi> reſolves to trouble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf no more with this ſort of Cattle, but now he was minded to hear, what the Chief Prieſts, and Rulers had to ſay of themſelves, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.13.</p>
            <p>You have brought this Man before me again, <hi>What have you to ſay againſt him?</hi> And finding they had no more
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:110425:36"/>to ſay, than what they had ſaid to <hi>Herod</hi> before, That he <hi>was a Receiver,</hi> and one that perverted the People from their Duty and Allegiance to the King, and calls himſelf a King: Says <hi>Pilate,</hi> I have been credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly informed, that in one of his Speeches he made to the People, he exhorted them quite contrary, to give <hi>Tribute to whom Tribute is due, Cuſtom to whom Cuſtom is due.</hi> And moreover, <hi>to give to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and to God the things that are Gods:</hi> And we have all read the Scriptures, and we know that they are all full, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound every where almoſt with Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of a Saviour, and of a <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and of a Chriſt, and of a King of the Jews, and this may be the Man, as far I know. This we are all ſure of, that he hath given ſhrewd Demonſtrations of his Godhead and Power, and why may he not be your King?</p>
            <p>Forthwith they all cry'd out with one Acclamation, <hi>We will have no King, but Caeſar:</hi> But hold, ſaith <hi>Pilate,</hi> If I muſt be his Judge, I muſt ground my Reaſons upon good, clear, full, and agreeable Evidence, before I can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:110425:37"/>him: I am not yet free to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, I profeſs plainly, I have great Anxities of Mind; and there is one thing that continually diſturbs my Mind of late, that I meet with in my Thoughts at every turn, and that is, That ſtrange Miracle that was wrought by him of late, which none of you can be ignorant of, and that is, the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Lazarus from the Dead, after he had been in the Grave four days, and began to ſtink:</hi> This is a very great thing, and a wonderful Miracle, let us rather permit him a while to go on farther with his Miracles, and if he be the Son of God, more and greater Wonders than theſe will appear, but if he be a <hi>Pſeudo-Chriſtus,</hi> a falſe Chriſt, or a falſe Prophet, we will immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemn him.</p>
            <p>But, ſay the Jews, if we let him go on thus, and he ſhould do more Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, <hi>the Romans will come in upon us, and take away from us both our Nation and Synagogues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaw, they ſtill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in this envious and malicious Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment, ſaith he, <hi>Ye have brought
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:110425:37"/>this Man here before me, as one that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth the people.</hi> Behold, Gentlemen! Silence in the Court, Cryer! I muſt ſpeak plainly, behold, there he ſtands, I have examined him according to the ſtrictneſs of the Law, and with as great Subtilty as I am capable of; and I have croſs-examin'd him, to ſee if I could trap him in his words; but I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs before you all, <hi>I find no fault at all in this man, touching thoſe things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you accuſe him.</hi> Nay, Silence, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, I pray, and hear me a little farther: You your ſelves very well know, I was willing to give you all the ſatisfaction, that poſſibly I could. I did not clear him, nor acquit him, the time before, tho' I might juſtly have done it; for there was nothing from your Accuſations, that was worthy of Bonds or Impriſonment, much leſs of Death; yet, to pleaſe you, ſeeing you were ſo eager of his Death, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, to ſatisfie my ſelf of <hi>Herod</hi>'s Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, I ſent you your ſelves with him bound before <hi>Herod,</hi> and I know you have no mean thoughts of <hi>Herod</hi>'s Judgment, and you know, I ſuppoſe,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110425:38"/>that his opinion was, <hi>That he found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worthy of Death in him,</hi> but hath return'd him back again to me, <hi>Luke</hi> 23, 11, 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will therefore chaſtiſe him, and let him go. Moreover, you know, that you have a Cuſtom, that I ſhould releaſe unto you one at the Paſſover, I will therefore releaſe unto you the King of the Jews; then they came all in, crowding at the Door, and crying at once with a lond voice, Away with this Man, and releaſe unto us Barabbas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Barabbas</hi> was one, that for <hi>Robbery</hi> and Murder in the City, was <hi>caſt into Priſon. Pilate, being willing to releaſe Jeſus, ſpake again to them. But they cry'd, ſaying, Crucifie him, Crucifie him,</hi> Matth. 23.19, 20, 21. <hi>Pilate</hi> reſolv'd then to ſee, if the following Severity, to the ever bleſſed <hi>Jeſu,</hi> would ſatisfie them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pilate then took Jeſus, and ſcourg'd him, and the Soldiers platted a Crown of Thorns, and put it upon his Head.</hi> Well might <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſay of the Sin of the Jews, <hi>Your Hands are defiled with Blood,</hi> for now were our bleſſed Saviour's Back and Sides all in a Gore-Blood; <hi>The Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:110425:38"/>of our Peace was upon him, and by bit Stripes we are boaled. Surely be bath born our Griefs, and carried our Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, yet we did eſteem him ſtricken, ſmitten of God, and afflicted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He is deſpiſed and rejected of Men, a Man of Sorrows, and acquainted with Grief,</hi> which made the Cry break out of his Sacred Mouth, <hi>Behold! If any Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row be like unto my Sorrow.</hi> And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> further tells, how his Diſciples would leave him at this time, <hi>And we hid</hi> (as it were) <hi>our Faces from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Soldiers platted a Crown of Thorns, and put it upon his Head, and they put on him again the Purple Robe that Herod had array'd him in, and ſaid, Hail, King of the Jews, and ſmote him with their hands, and, bowing he Knee, worſhipp'd him</hi> in Scorn and Deriſion to his Kingly Attire, with his Sacred Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples pouring down Blood, from the Crown of Thorns faſten'd into them, which made him ſay, The <hi>Arrows of the Almighty ſtick faſt in me!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lord! who is able to behold thee in this miſerable, ſcourg'd, and bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition? Thy Face beſmear'd
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:110425:39"/>and daub'd with the precious Blood of thy Sacred Temples, mix'd together with the filthy Excrements of the moſt naſty and polluted Wretches Spittle.</p>
            <p>How, O Lord, are thy Tender and Holy Back and Sides buffetted and bleeding with their Jewiſh Stripes, and thy Cheeks ſmitten with their filthy and brawny Hands. Who, Lord, is able to behold all this, and their Hearts not bleed, and even faint away, to ſee, how he is thus brought out, by <hi>Filate</hi>'s Command, before all the Jews, who lead him up and down by the Hair of his Head; Speaking of its Excellency and Beauty in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> where all his Graces are ſet forih, And <hi>his Hair, as black, and as buſhy as a Raven,</hi> now ſerves only as an Halter to lead him and drag him along.</p>
            <p>Then ſaith <hi>Pilate,</hi> Tho' I bring him forth to you thus mangled and torn, yet it is only to pleaſe and appeaſe you, but <hi>I find no fault in him,</hi> John 19.4. Then came Jeſus forth, wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Crown of Thorns and the Purple Robe, and <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaith unto them, <hi>Behold the Man,</hi> ver. 5. And
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:110425:39"/>this could not be acted, without a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy to the Jews.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your Hands are defiled with Blood,</hi> and your Fingers with Iniquity-Your Lips have ſpoken Lyes, and your Tongues have uttered perverſe Things. <hi>None calleth for Juſtice, nor any pleadeth for Truth. Their Feet run to Evil, and they make haſt to ſhed innocent Blood. Their Thoughts are Thoughts of Iniquity, Waſting and Deſtruction are in their Paths.</hi> Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is far from them, neither to do Juſtice doth it overtake them.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Judgment is turned away back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and Juſtice ſtandeth afar off, for Truth is fallen in the Street, and Equity cannot enter,</hi> Iſa. 59.</p>
            <p>And again, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith more to the ſame purpoſe, Yea, <hi>Truth fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and he that departeth from Evil</hi> (alluding to our Saviour) <hi>maketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Prey. And the Lord ſaw it, and it diſpleaſe him, that there was no Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:110425:40"/>And <hi>be ſaw there was no Man, and wonder'd that there was no Interceſſor, therefore his Arm brought Salvation unto him, and his Righteouſneſs ſuſtained him, for he put on Righteouſneſs as a Breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate, and as an Helmet of Salvation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Head, and be put on Garments of Vengeance for Cloathing, and was clad with Zeal as a Cloak. According to their Deeds, accordingly, be will repay Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to his Adverſaries, and Recompence to his Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we may ſee how the Spirit of God leads out the good Prophet, and not only him, but all the Patriarchs and Prophets; they are all full, and abound, with the Predictions and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figurations of <hi>Holy Jeſu;</hi> of the <hi>Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as;</hi> but more eſpecially this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah. Herod</hi> before, and the High-Prieſts and Soldiers now at this very time, cannot open their Mouths, and make Sport with our dear and ever-bleſſed Saviour, but it ſhall be foretold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Againſt whom do you ſport your ſelves? Againſt whom do you make a wide Mouth, and draw out the Tongue? Are you not
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:110425:40"/>Children of Tranſgreſſion, and a Seed of Falſhood?</hi> Yea, for <hi>Judas</hi> betraying him: For <hi>the Iniquity of his Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was I wrath, and ſmote him: I hid me, and was wrath, and he went on frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly</hi> in his Heart, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.4, 17.</p>
            <p>Now notwithſtanding all this, that <hi>Pilate</hi> had permitted them to do to innocent Jeſus, thinking, that this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity and Suffering of our Saviour, might have been full ſatisfaction to them all. When <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaid unto them, <hi>Behold the Man,</hi> in his Kingly Robes, thus affronted and abuſed in all this Contempt, Scorn and Sufferings. Yet was there inverate malice and envy, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt innocent and harmleſs Jeſus, ſuch, that all this Blood had not yet ſatisfied their Blood-thirſtineſs: But when the Chief Prieſts and Officers ſaw him, they cry'd out, all, This will not do, we muſt have him Crucify'd, nothing leſs than that will ſatisfie us. <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaith unto them, If nothing elſe will ſatisfie you, nor appeaſe this Tumult and Uproar, <hi>Take ye him and Crucifie him your ſelves, for I find no fault at all</hi> in him. This would not yet appeaſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:110425:41"/>them; <hi>for we have a Law, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our Law, we can put no Man to Death:</hi> Moreover, we have a ſtrict Law againſt Blaſphemy, not boring through the Tongue, but Death, and <hi>by our Law be ought to dye, becauſe be hath made himſelf the Son of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>When</hi> Pilate <hi>heard that Saying, he was the more afraid, and went into their Judgment-Hall</hi> a Third time,<note place="margin">Jeſus carried before <hi>Pilate</hi> a Third time.</note> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> 23.22. <hi>John</hi> 19.9 and ſaid unto Jeſus, <hi>Whence art thou?</hi> But <hi>Jeſus gave him him no Anſwer. Then</hi> Pilate <hi>ſaid unto him, Speakeſt thou not unto me? Knoweſt thou not, that I have power to Crucifie thee, and have power to Releaſe thee?</hi> How <hi>Pilate!</hi> is thy Power ſo great? And wilt thou not do it? Out of thy own Mouth ſhalt thou be condemn'd,<hi>John</hi> 19 10. <hi>Jeſus anſwer'd, and ſaid unto him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſebius,</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſt's Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, gloſes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. Chriſt's Divinity here, ſtoopt not to <hi>Pilate</hi>'s Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity.</note> 
               <hi>Thou couldeſt have no power at all againſt me, except it were given thee from above. From thenceforth</hi> Pilate <hi>ſought to Releaſe him, but the Jews
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:110425:41"/>cry'd out, ſaying, If thou let this Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, thou art not</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s Friend. Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever maketh himſelf a King, ſpeaketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Caefar. <hi>When</hi> Pilate <hi>therefore heard that Saying, he brought Jeſus forth, and ſate down in the Judgment Seat, in a place that is called the Pavement, but in the Hebrew</hi> Gabatha: <hi>And it was the preparation for the Paſſover, and about the ſixth hour, and he ſaith unto them, Behold your King! But they cry out, Away with him, Crucifie him.</hi> Pilate <hi>ſaith, Shall I Crucifie your King? The Chief Prieſts anſwered, We have no King but</hi> Caeſar, John 19.5.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Pilate</hi> when he ſaw that after all ways, and means, and courſes, that he had taken with Jeſus, to ſatisfie the Jews, nothing would do, leſs than to Crucifie him; He was now ready to paſs Sentence, and had enter'd the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Hall, and ſate down in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Seat, in order to it; his Wife ſends a Letter to him, with words to this effect. ſaying,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:110425:42"/>I beſeech you, Husband, if you have any Love for me, and any Bowels of Pity and compaſſion for this poor innocent Man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ula,</hi> his Wife, whom the Greek Church Honour as a Convert of our Lord's, ſends a Letter to him to this effect.</note> 
               <hi>Jeſus,</hi> (that now is arraign'd and ſtands before you juſt ready to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd, and Sentence to be paſs'd upon him, on purpoſe to gratifie the inordinate im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous deſires of a raſh Multitude, and blood-thirſty Jews,) forbear, I ſay, I humbly beg of you, and do not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn him, and <hi>have nothing to do with this juſt Man, for I have ſuffer'd many things for him this day in a Dream, which I ſhall communicate to you, as ſoon as I ſee you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>When</hi> Pilate <hi>ſaw this, and that he could prevail nothing, but rather that a Tumult was made, He called for Water and waſh'd his Hands before the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, ſaying, I am innocent of the Blood of this juſt Perſon, ſee you to it,</hi> Matth. 27.19, 24. <hi>Then anſwered all the People, and ſaid, Let his Blood be upon us and our Children for ever,</hi> if it will, we will
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:110425:42"/>have him Crucified. And <hi>the Voices of them and the Chief Prieſts prevailed, Luke</hi> 23.23.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Pilate releaſed Barabbas unto them, and delivor'd Jeſus to be Crucified, and they took him and lead him away,</hi> John 19.16. Then they called toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the whole Band of Soldiers, and with the Scarlet Robe, and <hi>the Crown of Thorns on his Head, they put a Reed in his right band,</hi> in ſtead of a Scepter, and <hi>they bowed the Knee before him, and ſaid, Hail, King of the Jews! And then they ſpit upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him, and took away the Reed from him, and ſmote him on the Head with it:</hi> And after they had done that, they mock'd him, and then they took <hi>off the Robe,</hi> that was upon him, by <hi>Herod</hi>'s Appointment; for to Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie him in that King-like Robe, would be a great diſhonour both to their King and Country.</p>
            <p>And the Saviour of the World now being left to the Barbarous Multitude to be Crucified,<note place="margin">The Jews and Gentiles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and aſſiſt in the Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of him, <hi>Mat. 20.18, 19.</hi>
               </note> and to do what they would with him. You may imagine,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:110425:43"/>with what Undecency and Rudeneſs they twiſt and turn about the Sacred Body of our Dear <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy moſt grievouſly ſore and ſtiff with Blood, from their late Inhuman Stripes, and with what force and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty they pull off his Robes, and put on his own Garments for his Crucifixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is enough to make a Devout Soul quake and tremble.</p>
            <p>Thus they took the ever-bleſſed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and <hi>led him away,</hi> bearing His own Croſs, toward Mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> or <hi>Golgotha,</hi> the <hi>place of a</hi> Skull, with all the Joy their Rage and Malice could invent.</p>
            <p>Stay now, my Soul, and take a ſerious view of thy Lord and Saviour, thus far afflicted,<note place="margin">The Devout Soul ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſee its Saviour paſs by to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Mount, the place of his Execution.</note> tormented, and forſaken. I ſay, now if thy Heart does not break to faſt, and the Sluces of thy Eyes do not pour down Pears too vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, take a view of him, and make a ſtand: It's the way to his Croſs, and he will come dragg'd by preſently.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:110425:43"/>O my Soul! be like the true. <hi>Zacheus,</hi> make the beſt of thy Ground to view, and of thy Time to conſider, for now the Agony of our Bleſſed Redeemer begins.</p>
            <p>Ah cruel and miſerable <hi>Pilate</hi> What haſt thou now done? And whom haſt thou Condemned? And whom haſt thou delivered up to be Crucified? The Lord of Glory. The Son of God! The Redeemer and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the World! A juſt Perſon! As thou thy ſelf hath teſtified of him. Thou found'ſt no Guile nor Evil in his Mouth. What canſt thou expect from him then for thy own Salvation! See but yonder, how he is hal'd and dragg'd away from thee, with his Head crown'd with Thorns, his Temples bleeding, his Face beſmear'd with Blood and Spittle, from the baſeſt and vileſt of the poor ignorant Jews, and his Back ſtooping under the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of his own Croſs, and his poor Legs trembling, by reaſon of its weight, which, with the Duſt, Dirt, Crowd, Sweat, Blood, and want of Suſtenance
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:110425:44"/>to revive his poor droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirits,<note place="margin">His ſacred Lips having received no nouriſhment from the time of the Paſſover till the time of his thirſting up on the Croſs, which was the third day, and exactly forerun the time of his Body ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Grave.</note> is ready to ſink, Canſt thou look after him, <hi>Pilate,</hi> and ſee all this, and thy Heart and Soul not faint and bleed?</p>
            <p>What wouldſt thou give, <hi>Pilate,</hi> now, to recal thy wicked and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Sentence of a juſt Perſon, thus ſpitefully uſed and dealt with? <hi>Like a Lamb to the Slaughter, or a Sheep before the Shearers is dumb, ſo openeth he not his Mouth,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, not for Pity to his tender Back,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Simon</hi> the Cyrenian compell'd to bear our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Croſs.</note> but for fear he tire before he come to the Place of ſuffering, and that they may give him ſome eaſe to lengthen out his Torments, and that they may be able to inflict more Stripes upon him, and that he may more become the publick view, and that he may be the better come at to receive his
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:110425:44"/>Stripes, and to be ſpit upon, and thrown at, let us ſeize and compel the <hi>Traveller,</hi> Simon <hi>of</hi> Cyrenia <hi>to bear his Croſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O, happy art thou, <hi>Simon,</hi> to bear thy Lord's Croſs! Let there be no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs in thee. Thou hadſt no hand in Condemning him, nor Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with Thorns, nor ſpitting upon him, nor buſſetting him; let it not grieve thee, thou may'ſt be am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply rewarded for thy pains, if thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveſt in him; He, in requital, will bear thy Soul to Heaven for thee. How many poor Souls, now a days, would have been glad to have ſuffer'd for him, or with him, that have already found part of the Virtue of his Death and Reſurrection?</p>
            <p>But how can I blame thee, poor <hi>Simon,</hi> when all his Diſciples <hi>had left him,</hi> and one of them was he that <hi>betray'd him</hi> to this, but all <hi>hid their Faces</hi> from him, as he himſelf had foretold them. <hi>And ye ſhall leave me alone, but I am not alone, becauſe the Father is with me.</hi> O, dear Lord Jeſu, joyful is this News to me, that I now here thee
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:110425:45"/>ſpeak, That thou haſt the Preſence, Comforts, and Aſſiſtance of thy Father, of thy God, with thee in this hour, in this great Agony and Suffering.</p>
            <p>And having thus far mournfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied our Lord and Saviour up the Hill, laden with Afflictions and Sorrows, to the top of Mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> where the Croſs of our dear Saviour is to be fix'd, for the ſeparating of his moſt Glorious Soul and moſt Precious Body. Who can but conſider, and be amaz'd, to think, what ſtupendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sorrows and Sufferings our dear Lord, at this moment, feels and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends?</p>
            <p>All Malefactors that we have at any time beheld with our Chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate Eyes; there are three Times eſpecially, that conflict and operate moſt upon ſympathizing Beholders; and according as the Sentence for the extinguiſhing part of Life is, ſo are we more or leſs affected, and afflicted with Sorrow.</p>
            <p>Firſt, at the time of their Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and dreadful Sentence, <q>Thou ſhalt return to the Place from whence
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:110425:45"/>thou cameſt, and from thence to the Place of Execution, and there be hang'd by the Neck till thou art dead, or Quarter'd alive, or burnt to Death, and the Lord have Mercy upon thy Soul.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, at the preſent time of their going up the Ladder, or being faſtned to the Rack, Croſs, Stake or Block. What Eyes can behold this, but their Face ſhall gather Paleneſs and Sorrow,<note place="margin">A ſimpathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</note> and their Knees even knock to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, to think what is at hand, and they now going immediately to ſuffer.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, at the time of their being in the very preſent Agony of Death, where, not only the preſent Torment of Body they endure, but the dreadful Terrors of an affrighted Conſcience at the immediate ſight of a revengeful God, and irreconcileable Judge, that is now ready to caſt both Soul and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy into Hell-Fire, do produce Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. And this is the preſent and perfect ſtate and condition of all Men,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:110425:46"/>by reaſon of Sin. For this, and this alone, is our dear Lord and Saviour conflicted in the Garden, even to the extracting great drops of Blood trick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down his moſt ſacred Hands and Face.</p>
            <p>And when he ſaw, his moſt Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Father would not reverſe this eternal Decree and Puniſhment to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind for Sin, without his own ever bleſſed Son's undergoing and ſuffering Death and Hell for us. Saith he, <hi>If this bitter Cup ſhall not paſs from me without drinking of it, Thy Will be done. A Body haſt thou prepar'd,</hi> that is mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Croſs, and ready and willing to ſuffer all the Miſery and Torment, that the moſt cruel Rage and Malice of Men and Devils, and an enraged God, will permit to inflict, rather than poor Man ſhall ſuffer the deep Preſſures of Thy Eternal Wrath and Indignation, in that <hi>Luke that burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with Fire and Brimſtone for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O, bleſſed Father! Thou art my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from all Eternity; and am not I thy Son? <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.23. <hi>I was from
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:110425:46"/>everlaſting, before ever the Earth was. While as yet he bad not made the Earth or the Fields, nor the higheſt part of the Duſt of the World. When be prepared the Heavens, I was there. When he ſet a Compaſs upon the face of the Deep. When be eſtabliſhed the Clouds above. When he ſtrengthen'd the Fountains of the Deep. When he gave to the Sea his Decree, That the Waters ſhould not paſs his Commandment. When he appointed the Foundations of the Earth: Then was I by him, as one brought up with him, and I was daily his Delight, rejoycing always before him. Rejoycing in the habitable parts of his Earth; And my Delights were with the Sons of Men;</hi> when thou createdſt them in a ſtate of Innocency and Perfection. And, O, Heavenly Father, ſhall I now forſake them, in a ſtate of Sin and Miſery and Eternal Deſtruction? No, O Holy Father, <hi>for this very end did I come into the World;</hi> I, that immaculate Lamb, ſlain from the beginning, conceiv'd by the Holy Ghoſt, born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> as to human Nature, am toucht with their Infirmities, and therefore
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:110425:47"/>came to ſuccour poor tempted Souls. I know the Devil's Wrath and Power, and continual Attempts to all Mankind. For this cauſe was I carry'd into the Wilderneſs, endur'd Hunger and Cold, Faſting and Temptations, and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſuccour and relieve, and at laſt deliver, thoſe that are tempted.</p>
            <p>As Man, I my ſelf, O Righteous Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, had fell by his Temptation; but, as God, I overcame him, and can I let them ſuffer, when I know Man is not ſufficient of himſelf to overcome the Devil nor Sin, nor the Power of Death and Hell, nor thy Eternal Wrath and Diſpleaſure. This was the Eternal Decree of the great Council of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from everlaſting, That ſeeing Man was not able to recover his loſt ſtate, That Man born of a Virgin, conceived from his God-like Power by the Holy Ghoſt overſhadowing her, in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of time ſhould be born, the Son of God, fully qualifi'd God-Man, to make compleat Satisfaction and Atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for laps'd Man, to the unſatisfi'd Juſtice, and incenſed Wrath and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:110425:47"/>And for this Cauſe was I Born here on Earth, and left the Boſom of my Heavenly Father, and all Thrones and Dominions, Principalities and Powers of Glorified Saints and Angels, and took upon me Human Nature, and came cheerfully leaping over the Hills, and skipping over the Mountains, <hi>as a Roe, or young Hart upon the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Spices.</hi> For this <hi>Cauſe came I,</hi> as in <hi>the Volume of the Book it is written of me, to do thy Will, O God,</hi> That poor Man might not be Eternally loſt, but thy incens'd Wrath might be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peas'd, full ſatisfaction might be made, the power of Hell might be broke, and Devils themſelves reſerved in Hell, bound in Chains of Darkneſs, until the great Day, and poor fallen Man acquitted and diſcharg'd, and his Soul Eternally Sav'd.</p>
            <p>This is Love indeed! unbounded, unlimited, Love! infinite, inexhauſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, incomprehenſible Love of the Son of God, the ever bleſſed Redeemer of the World. <hi>O, the Height, Length, Breadth and Depth of the Goodneſs of God</hi> to Mankind! This is tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:110425:48"/>Love, Love without compariſon! Now, what muſt all this extort from us? To ſee our dear Lord and Saviour juſt now mounting the Croſs, giving of himſelf up to the utmoſt Cruelty, that the wickedneſs of Men and Devils can inflict upon him, from the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency and Poiſon of their moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Rage, and all this for our Sins, and to ſet us free.</p>
            <p>Here is the Sentence of <hi>Pilate;</hi> 
               <q>Take him, ſcourg'd already, accord-to your Cuſtom, and bound, Take him and Crucifie him, with this Inſcription over his Head,<note place="margin">That every one that paſſeth by might un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it.</note> written in Latin, Greek, and Hebrew, <hi>This is Ieſus of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth King of the Iews.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The Death of the Croſs was the ancient Puniſhment of the Jews for their moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Malefactors,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Cave<hi>'s</hi> Primitive Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s time, and therefore eſteemed by the accurſed Jews, moſt fit for our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to dye by. Omitting all the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:110425:48"/>various Forms and different kinds, which were all us'd towards the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, there were two things in this way of ſuffering rendred it very ſevere, <hi>viz.</hi> the Pain and Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy of it. Painful it muſt needs be, becauſe the Party ſuffering was faſtned to it with Nails drove through his Hands and Feet, the moſt ſenſible parts of Man, from ſuch a vaſt quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Nerves and Sinews uniting and terminating in thoſe places: And they were pierc'd only in thoſe extream Parts, ſo far diſtant from the Heart, on purpoſe that the exquiſiteneſs of their Torments and Death, might be the more lingring and tedious. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that ſome, out of tender Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, have cauſed ſome to be ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before they were Crucified, as <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> did the Pirats he had ſworn to execute on the Croſs; <hi>Sueton. in Vit. Caeſar.</hi> Cap. 47. p. 76. But no ſuch Favour was ſhewn to Chriſtians; they were ſuffer'd to remain, during all theſe cruciating Pangs, till mere Hunger ſtarv'd them, or the Mercy of wild Beaſts, or Birds of Prey, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcht
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:110425:49"/>them. Thus <hi>St. Andrew</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd two whole days upon the Croſs. <hi>Martyrol. Rom. p,</hi> 736.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Timotheus</hi> and his Wife <hi>Maura,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many other Torments, hung upon the Croſs nine days together, before they compleated their Martyrdom. Nor was the Shame of this way of Suffering leſs than the Pain of it; Crucifixion being the puniſhment of Slaves, Traitors, and the vileſt of Malefactors: Inſomuch, that for a Free man to dye thus, was accounted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, the higheſt Degree of Ignominy and Reproach imaginable. Therefore the Roman Hiſtorians call'd it <hi>Servile Supplicium,</hi> a puniſhment on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proper for Slaves. But this pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Croſs <hi>Conſtantine</hi> took away, out of Reverence to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, not being willing, that that ſhould be the puniſhment of the vileſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors, which had been the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereon the Son of God had purchas'd Salvation for Mankind. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zom. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 418.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:110425:49"/>But now, O holy Jeſu, muſt thou be lifted up to ſuffer and dye upon the Croſs, as it was Propheſi'd of thee.<note place="margin">Chriſts nail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Croſs.</note> 
               <hi>As the Serpent was lifted up in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo ſhall the Son of Man be lifted up.</hi> Now, O bleſſed Jeſu, who is able to ſee thee, and behold thee, how with rude hands and ſear'd Hearts they force and twiſt, pull, hale, and extend thy Sacred Hands, that were always doing of good, and healing Diſeaſes, now nailing to the Croſs? Who can but mourn and lament bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, as not being able to behold thee, the Lord of Life. Our Souls within us muſt be pierc'd, and even our Hearts break in pieces, to ſee thy ever bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Feet thus extended and rackt, and nail'd to the Croſs, and to think what Agony and Torment they now endure, that always kept the ſteady Paths of thy God in the ready way to Man's Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>Now, to ſee thee <hi>tread the Wine-Preſs alone,</hi> and of all the People there was none with thee. And as thou thy ſelf ſaid'ſt, <hi>I look'd, and there was none
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:110425:50"/>to help; and I wondred, and there was none to uphold; therefore my own Arm brought Salvation to me, and my fury up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold me. In all their Afflictions, I was afflicted, and the Angel of his preſence ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. In his Love, and in his Pity he Redeem'd them, and be bore them and carry'd them all the days of old.</hi> Thus the tender care and Pity of Chriſt was towards his Children and People from the beginning, it bore Date in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of Heaven.</p>
            <p>And now, dear Jeſu, to ſee how with uncontroli'd Severity they pierce thy very Hands and Feet, and pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate into thy very Nerves and Sinews, not only forcing thy ſacred Blood out of thy tender and del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cate Veins, but ſqueezing it out upon the very Croſs; And all this for me, O Lord, and for my great and grievous Sins, that are numberleſs, doſt thou endure this grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous torment, and ſhed infinite drops of Blood, crying out in the bitterneſs of thy Soul, <hi>Behold, and ſee, if there be any Sorrows lie my Sorrows.</hi> O Lord, who is able to ſee thee, bleeding, and groaning, and crying, and dying for
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:110425:50"/>me, and not Weep and mourn, and diſſolve into Tears and Sorrow? Or, rather than my ſpent Eyes ſhould want Tears, help my Heart, O Lord, to weep Tears of Blood. Who can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, O Lord, when I conſider every Sigh, every Groan, every Cry, every Tear, every drop of Blood, every Pang, every Pain, every Twitch, every Convulſion, and every Diſtortion that thou endureſt, are the products and effects of my Sin. O Lord, let never a Minute be loſt, nor never a Thought be ſpent in vain, now my Saviour is dying, and bleeding on the Croſs.</p>
            <p>And thus ſhould every devout Soul endeavour to do, when they come to the Table and Supper of the Lord, that being the chiefeſt time to give the ſtrongeſt and livelieſt ſtrokes in our Hearts and Souls, of the compleateſt Reſemblance and Commemoration of our dear Lord and Saviour's Suffering and dying on the Croſs for us; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how his Body was broken, and his Blood guſhing out for us, for our Sins and for our Salvation. <hi>This do,</hi> (as our dear Saviour's Words are) <hi>as oft
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:110425:51"/>as you do it, in remembrance of me,</hi> knowing that thus Chriſt dy'd for thee.</p>
            <p>And now, O holy Jeſu, help my poor crippl'd Soul through the Crowd,<note place="margin">The earneſt Petition of a truly ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thizing gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soul.</note> to lay it ſelf down at the foot of thy Croſs, to receive the drops of Blood, as they come trickling down from thy Wounds, into my Polluted Soul, that not one drop of thy moſt precious Blood be ſpilt on the ground, or the ſacred Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor of Eternal Life be waſted or loſt. O Lord! Who is able to behold thee longer? O that I could bleed, die, and pour out my Soul with thee!</p>
            <p>Happy art thou, wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Thief,<note place="margin">The Thief upon the Croſs rebuk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, and timely pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</note> that was reſerv'd till this time, to have the Lord of Life to ſuffer with thee, to have his Jewiſh ignominy thy poor Souls advantage, to hear now thy Prayers, and ſave thy Soul from Eternal Death. Let thy curſed Companion and Malefactor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in his obſtinacy and incredulity, with the reſt of the wicked <hi>Jews,</hi> cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:110425:51"/>and reviling his Saviour, and going head-long to Hell. <hi>If thou be Chriſt, come down from the Croſs, and ſave thy ſelf and us.</hi> Well as it done, O Thief, that thou ſo timely rebuk'd him. <hi>Why doſt thou not now fear God, ſeeing thou art in the ſame condemnation,</hi> and ſame ſuffering? We, thou knoweſt, <hi>ſuffer juſtly for our Offences, but this Man hath done nothing amiſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot admoniſh nor perſuade thee longer; my Soul is juſt ready to expire, and I am juſt fainting away. A mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment loſt now is loſt for ever. My time is but ſhort to pray for my own Soul, that am loaded and crowded with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of Iniquities and Sins. If thou wilt die obſtinately; Lord, help me to die penitently; If thou wilt continue in Contempt; help me, Lord, to continue in Faith and Patience. If thou look'ſt upon him as a Deceiver I look upon him as my Saviour. If thou abound'ſt in reviling, and ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (the opportunity now offer'd) I will abound to my laſt breath with ſtrong Prayers and Tears, to the very laſt gaſp, crying and calling to my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:110425:52"/>and ever-Bleſſed Redeemer, and King, Lord have mercy upon me quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, quickly, O Holy Jeſu, or I periſh for ever; and <hi>remember me when thou com'ſt into the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Bleſſed Jeſu, that art ſo ready to give out Pardons and Remiſſions to poor Penitent Sinners, that call and cry to thee at the very laſt gaſp: As ſoon as they ask, it is thy own Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Promiſe, <hi>Ask, and ye ſhall receive. Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away, but not one jot or tittle of thy Sacred Word, or Promiſe, ſhall paſs away. Verily, Verily, thou ſhalt be with me this day in Paradiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the time of Repentance; this is the time of effectual Prayers; this is the time of weeping and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Sin; this is the time of drench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bathing thy Soul in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Heart-blood and Life of thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. It's no matter, what the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed <hi>Jews</hi> ſay, in reviling and mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Son of God, their King, their Saviour, and Redeemer. <hi>They that paſs'd by, rail'd, and wagg'd their beads, ſaying, Ah! Thou that deſtroy'ſt the Temple, and in three days build it up
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:110425:52"/>again, come down from the Croſs, and ſave thy ſelf, it thou canſt. Let Chriſt the King of</hi> Iſrael <hi>deſcend now from the Croſs, that we may ſee and believe.</hi> If thou be the King of the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſavethy ſelf.</p>
            <p>O Lord! Let the wicked <hi>Jews</hi> be now making up the number of their Sins through Infidelity, till the time of Repentance is paſt, and the Door is ſhut. I will be ſtill calling and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my God. Let them in ſcorn and deriſion be Crucifying my Saviour between two Malefactors, as the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of them. I, in the greateſt bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my Soul, will be pouring out the moſt ardent of my Prayers with Sighs, Groans, and Tears, that are unutterable, to remember me, both now whilſt thou art on the Croſs, and as ſoon as thou art exalted in thy Kingdom of Glory.</p>
            <p>O God! the Son, Redeemer of the World, have mercy upon me, miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sinner. By the myſtery of thy Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Incarnation; By thy Nativity and Circumciſion; By thy Faſting, Baptiſm, and Temptation, Good Lord, deliver me. By thy Agony, and Bloody Sweat;
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:110425:53"/>By the Croſs and Paſſion; By thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Death and Burial; By thy Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rions Reſurrection and Aſcenſion; And by the coming of the Holy Ghoſt, Good Lord, deliver me. O Son of God! I beſeech thee to hear me! O Lamb of God! that <hi>takeſt away the Sins of the World,</hi> Grant me thy Peace! O Chriſt! hear me! O Lord, hear me! O Lamb of God that takeſt away the Sins of the World, have Mercy upon me! Lord, have mercy upon me! Chriſt, have mercy upon me! O Lord, hear me, and remember me, now, now, thou art giving up thy moſt precious Life, and pouring out thy innocent, harmleſs, and compaſſionate Soul. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member me, when thou com'ſt into thy Kingdom. What can a poor Soul beg more, and deſire more of its Redeemer at the point of Death? Or what can be given, or done more, by an ever-bleſſed Saviour and Holy Jeſu, to ſave us from the Jaws of Death, Power of Hell, and Eternal Torments? Than to be pouring out his own Soul by Prayers and Tears to his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, at the very laſt minute of his precious Life for us?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:110425:53"/>But ſtay, O bleſſed Jeſu! What is it I perceive and ſee ſtill in this black and diſmal hour? O Lord! Is it thee ſtill in thy Agony, and bloody Sweat? It is ſo dark, I can but juſt perceive thee. Is it not finiſht yet? What ſay'ſt thou, Lord, now to my poor, fainting, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Soul? Speak, Lord, one word of comfort to me, notwithſtanding all thy Adverſaries and implacable Enemies about thee. <hi>Speak,</hi> Lord, and <hi>thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant heareth. Speak,</hi> Lord, and <hi>my Soul ſhall live.</hi> If thou art ſo faint, thou can'ſt not ſpeak in this grievous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, let thy good Prophet ſpeak for thee.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, when I came, was there no man to help? When <hi>I call'd, was there none to anſwer?</hi> Do you think, I am paſt Saving of you, or Delivering of you, in this time of my Dereliction? Tho you all forſake me in this hour of my Crucifixion, I do not forſake you, my Children, my Flock, and my poor Lambs, my Redeemed, and the purchas'd of my Soul. <hi>Is my Hand ſhortned at all?</hi> though nail'd to the Croſs? <hi>that I cannot Save, or that I
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:110425:54"/>cannot Redeem?</hi> Or, have I no power to deliver? Behold, at my Rebuke, <hi>I dry up the Sea. I make the Rivers a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs. The Fiſh ſtinketh and dieth for Thirſt, becauſe there is no Water. I cloath the Heavens with blackneſs, and I make Sack loth their covering. I make the Earth to quake and tremble, and it would tumble down to the Eternal Abiſs, but that I bear up the Pillars of it,</hi> at this very moment, that I am bleeding and dying upon the Croſs. Let the <hi>Jews</hi> have as vile and mean thoughts of me as they pleaſe, and caſt all their ſcorn and malice, mixt with their cruel rage and poiſon, at me: It's I, that make the <hi>Rocks to rent, the Sun to gather pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Moon to be turn'd into Blood:</hi> Notwithſtanding, that all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures might be fulfill'd, and my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd Ones, the Purchas'd of my Soul, ſet at liberty, <hi>I give my Back to the ſmiters, and my Cheeks to them that pluck't off my Hair. I hid not my face from ſhame and ſpitting; for the Lord G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d doth and will help my Soul, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain it,</hi> Whatever my Body doth, or ſhall cry out, and ſay; therefore <hi>I
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:110425:54"/>ſhall not be confounded;</hi> therefore I have <hi>ſet my Face like a Flint, and know that I ſhall not be aſham'd. He is near, that juſtifieth me: Who will contend with me? Let us ſtand together. Who is my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary? Let him come near. Behold, the Lord will help me, Who is he, that will condemn me? Lo! they ſhall all wax old as a Garment, and the Moth ſhall eat them up. Who is it amongſt you that feareth the Lord? Who obeyeth the Voice of hit Servant, that walketh in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and hath no light? Let him truſt in the Name of the Lord, and ſtay him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upod his God. Behold all ye that kindle a Five, that compaſs your ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with ſparks, walk in the light of your Fire, and in the ſparks that ye have kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, this ſhall ye have of my hand, ye ſhall lie down in ſorrow.</hi> Iſa. 50.</p>
            <p>But, my Soul, draw near, or elſe thou wilt loſe the ſight of thy Saviour. Darkneſs haſtens on a-pace. O Holy Jeſu, is it not thee? Let me wipe, and drain, my dim, and almoſt ſpent, and blind Eyes, and look again. Lord! it is thee. I ſtill perceive thy Tears diſtilling down thy ſacred Face; Thy
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:110425:55"/>Temples boiling out of Spirituous Blood; Thy Sacred Hands and Feet blubbering up, and venting out from behind the Nails, great Bladders of Blood and Froth, from the expulſive force of thy moſt exquiſite Torments. O Lord! even now my Soul fainteth and dieth within me. My Spirits fail me. My poor Mortal Eyes, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, fainting, Heart, is not able to behold thee longer. Nor yet, while my Life and Strength remains, can I forbear (when an interval of Tears will permit my ſight,) looking after thee ſtill, and pouring forth my fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, and frequent, requeſts to thee; and falling into theſe moſt ſtrict Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations within my ſelf.</p>
            <p>What! From the Sixth, till almoſt the Ninth Hour, is my dear Saviour in the height of this vehement Agony, and not over, yet? But ſtill labouring and groaning under the burthen of my Sins? What great and heinous Sin of mine is it, that I am guilty of, that is not aton'd yet? That God is ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely incens'd at, and that he will not yet pardon? That my poor Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our is yet ſtruggling for, till the laſt
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:110425:55"/>drop of his moſt Precious Blood is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted? Let me look immediately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Soul, into every corner and crany of it, all muſt out, and be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd, of what nature or quality ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be, whether Lying, Curſing, Swearing and Forſwearing, Theft, Murther, Fornication, Adultery, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt, Pollution with the Dead, or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation with Beaſts, Blaſphemy, Spite and Contempt againſt thy Holy Word and Sacraments.</p>
            <p>O quickly, quickly, quickly, help me, O my God, to find it out, and to bring all to remembrance, that thou mayeſt no longer be extorted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vuls'd in theſe grievous Torments. Look upon me, dear Saviour, and caſt quickly thy dying Eye to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me,<note place="margin">Chriſt caſt his dying Eyes to a Supplicant Sinner.</note> as thou didſt upon <hi>Peter,</hi> in the High-Prieſt's Hall, denying thee, that I may immediately remember it, ſeeing thy Righteous Father is ſo exact and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, that there is no Redemption of thy moſt precious Soul, and Sacred Body, from the Croſs, till thou haſt paid the very utmoſt Farthing, and haſt
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:110425:56"/>made full and compleat Satisfaction for me.</p>
            <p>O, dear Lord! That Caſt of thy languiſhing, diſtracted, dying Eye, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, hath brought all to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. And there, dear Saviour, in the ſpeedy conveyance of a moſt ardent Ejaculation, is it moſt humbly and devoutly preſented unto thee, that thou mayeſt inſtantly be deliver'd from the Torments and Bondage of Death, in making ample Atonement for it, and my poor Soul may be recorded, as ſoon as thou art exalted in thy Kingdom of Glory.</p>
            <p>Stay, O my Soul! a ſmall ſpace longer, for now Darkneſs haſtens on amain, that I can ſcarce ſee thee: But what is it I hear? Does this abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sin of mine ſtick ſo faſt ſtill in the ſtrict Court of Heaven, that it makes thee cry out thus? Will it not yet be diſcharg'd? What dreadful Cry is it? I'm ſure, it muſt be my Sin. Thou, O bleſſed <hi>Jeſu!</hi> art Spotleſs, and without Sin. <hi>Guile was not found in thy Mouth:</hi> It muſt be mine; O miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and wretched Creature as I am! How impoſſible was I, and unable, to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:110425:56"/>have under went this Suffering and Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for my Sin; as a poor Worm, Duſt &amp; Aſhes, and ſinful polluted Man, when it makes the Son of God thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, and cry out Hark! Hark! O my Soul, what is it that ſounds thus in my Ears? 'Tis no uſual Cry; it muſt come from my Tortur'd Redeemer. Hark! Harſt! Silence! Hark! What is't? <hi>Eloi, Eloi, Lama ſabachthani! My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> O my Soul, what is it? What is it I hear? <hi>Eloi, Eloi, Lama-ſabachthani? My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> O Lord! O God! O Saviour! O ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſſed Redeemer! O my Chriſt! Son of God! Lamb of God! Dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of the Father! Where ſhall I go? Where ſhall I hide my ſelf from the Wrath and dreadful Diſpleaſure of thy Father, if thou cry'ſt out ſo, that art his Son, his only begotten Son, in whom always he was ſo well pleas'd? What then can I do, or where ſhall I appear, if Wrath break out never ſo little to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, when thou, that art a God, complains ſo bitterly? What then muſt a poor, vile, wretched, miſerable, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done Creature, and grievous polluted Sinner, do?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:110425:57"/>But ſtay, my Soul! Endeavour ſtill to be looking up toward thy Saviour. Let my tremblng, fainting Heart, ſtill endure the Crowd. If thou dyeſt here, thou mayeſt ſtill be remembred with the Penitent Thief. It's the only time and place under Heaven, to give up a departing Soul; but if otherwiſe thou art called for a longer time on Earth, have patience, and ſee the laſt of thy erer-bleſſed Saviour. If the Mother of our ever-bleſſed Lord ſtand to ſee the laſt Gaſp of her dearly beloved Son, and if <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſtand weeping, and crying, and praying, to ſee the laſt Gaſp, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal End, of this unparalell'd Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, thou haſt as much need. I ſay, if, amongſt theſe, <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of our ever-bleſſed <hi>Jeſu,</hi> can ſtand to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold her Nine Months Labour in her precious Womb, and to ſee the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail of her Soul thus tormented to Death, canſt not thou do the ſame? More eſpecially, thy Sins, O my Soul, are great, which thou haſt committed; have patience a while, and much ſhall be forgiven thee.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:110425:57"/>Let us now ſee, what further the Jews have to do, till their Wrath is quite ſpent.</p>
            <p>And <hi>when the Sixth Hour was come, there was Darkneſs over the whole Earth, until the Ninth Hour; and at the Ninth Hour, Jeſus cry'd out with a loud Voice, ſaying, Eloi, Eloi, Lama ſabachthani! Which, being interpreted, is, My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me? And ſome of them which ſtood by, ſaid, He calleth for Elias, let him come down and ſave him, if he can. Then preſently he cry'd, I Thirſt; immediately one runs, and fills a Spunge full of Vinegar and Gaul, and gives it him to drink,</hi> Pſal. 69.21. Mark 15.23.</p>
            <p>All this Suffering hitherto of our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour, had wrought nothing upon theſe Cruel, Incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, Jewiſh, Stony Hearts, but they ſqueeze this bitter Potion into his moſt Sacred Mouth with bitter Revilings, which at all times is counted moſt baſe and inhuman, to inſult over the moſt vileſt Malefactors, at the time of their ſuffering the ſatisfaction and penalty of the Law; yet ſuch is the Cruelty
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:110425:58"/>of theſe barbarous Infidels; Let us ſee, ſay they, if <hi>Elias</hi> will come and take him down from the Croſs, and ſave him.</p>
            <p>But our Bleſſed <hi>Jeſu,</hi> as he had liv'd Chriſt the Son of the ever living God, ſo he would dye Chriſt and Saviour of the World, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aying for his moſt bitter and inhuman Enemies, at the very laſt minute of his moſt precious Life. <hi>Father, forgive them, they know not what they do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when they ſaw, that all their Rage, Malice, and Barbarous Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ended in a Prayer for them, their Hearts began to ſmite them, and they ſtood gazing one upon another; and when they began to ſee ſuch thick Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs fall upon them, and the Earth quaking and trembling under their Feet, they began to be convinc'd in their Conſciences, ſome of them, and to ſay one to another, <hi>Surely, this is the Son of God,</hi> and cry'd, What ſhall we do. And looking up to Jeſus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, they ſaw him bowing his Head, and ſaying, <hi>Conſummatum eſt, Now it is finiſhed: Father, into thy hands I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:110425:58"/>my Spirit, and bowed his Head, and gave up the Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, as one devoutly obſerves, the poſture of this Death carries in it a lively Repreſentation of his great Love to Mankind, his Arms ſtretch'd out, as it were, to embrace all thoſe that would come to him, and his Head bowing down to kiſs them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And at the Ninth Hour there was Darkneſs over the whole Earth,</hi> for the Sun began to hide his Head, as not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to behold it: <hi>The Vail of the Temple was torn from the top to the bottom, the Earth quak'd, and the Rocks rent, which made the Centurion</hi> that ſtood by as a Sheriff, by <hi>Pilate</hi>'s Command, to ſee our Saviour executed, begin to be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly afraid, and to ſay, <hi>Of a certain, this was the Son of God,</hi> Luke 23.30. Matth. 27.54.</p>
            <p>And no ſooner had our dear Saviour let fly his Bleſſed Spirit, and aſcended to his Heavenly Throne, and glorified Saints and Angels, but they, rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing at his glorious Preſence, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately brake forth into ſinging of Praiſes and Hallelujahs, with the Penitent
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:110425:59"/>Thief. And having now overcome the Power of Death and <hi>Hell, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Graves open'd, and many Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Saints, which ſlept, aroſe,</hi> Matth. 27.52. and began to <hi>glorifie God,</hi> Like 23.47. But the Jews, when they ſaw all this, began to call to the <hi>Mountains, to hide them from the Wrath to come;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 23.48.</note> And <hi>all the People that came together to that Sight, beheld the things that were done, and were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maz'd,</hi> and ſmote their Breaſts, and return'd, that the Scriptures might be fulfill'd; <hi>They ſhall look upon me whom they have pierced, and they ſhall mourn for him as one mourneth for his Son, and ſhall be in bitterneſs for him, as one that is in bitterneſs for his Firſt-born,</hi> Zech. 12.10.</p>
            <p>This made <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Athens</hi> to ſay, (being in <hi>Aegypt</hi> at the ſame time of our Saviour's ſuffering,) when he ſaw this great Eclipſe of the Sun, contrary as at other times, cry out, and ſay, <hi>Aut Deus natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae patitur, vel Mundi Machina diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetur; Either the World was at an
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:110425:59"/>end, or the Maker of it ſuffer'd great Agony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, O my Soul, what haſt thou more to do, but to attend till thy Saviour is took down from the Croſs, and, with the remainder of thy feeble Strength, and almoſt-ſpent Eyes, accompany his precious Body to his Funeral, which will be ſolemniz'd this Evening?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Jews therefore, becauſe it was the Preparation for the Sabbath, and Even was come, and they had a Cuſtom among themſelves, That Bodies ſhould not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main upon the Croſs on the Sabbath-day, eſpecially at this time, it being a great and high Day, the Day of the Great Paſſover; the Soldiers therefore came to</hi> Pilate, <hi>and beſought him, that the Bodies of the Malefactors might be taken down from the Croſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John,</hi> the Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Diſciple, to whoſe Care Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath'd his Mother, ſaw this, and bore Record of it, that we might believe, John <hi>19.35.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and their Legs broken;</hi> which no ſooner was granted, but one of the Soldiers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding ſtill with his inveterate Malice more than the reſt, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:110425:60"/>the wonderful Miracles he had ſo lately ſeen from the Glorious Sun of the Firmament, vailing its Head, the Earth trembling, the very Rocks breaking in pieces, and the Vail of the Temple (the moſt Sacred<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Place of their Worſhip,) rent from the top to the bottom; yet he takes no notice of all this, but forthwith runs with his Spear in his hand, and violently pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the tender Side of our dear Lord and Saviour, and immediately <hi>guſh'd out Water and Blood,</hi> the Emblems of the Two abiding Sacraments, that our Lord left with us, in commemoration of His Bleſſed Humanity and Divinity, Baptiſm, and the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Supper. And this could not be done without a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, <hi>In that Day, there ſhall be a Fountain open for the Houſe of David, and Inhabitants of Jeruſalem, to waſh in, for Sin and for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs,</hi> Zach. 13.1.</p>
            <p>And when they took down the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the other Two Malefactors, found they were not dead, and brake their Legs. The Jews having a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom amongſt them, to break the Legs
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:110425:60"/>of the Crucify'd Perſons, when they took them down from the Croſs, if they ſound they had any Life in them. But <hi>when they came to Jeſus, and found that he was already dead,</hi> probably from the vaſt expenſion of Spirits, ſo much exhauſted and waſted, from his former<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sufferings, and for want of Reſpit, and freſh recruit of Suſtenance, (for which we do not read, from the time of his Betraying, to the time of his Paſſion, of Care or Supply from any.) Or perhaps from the wound of the Spear in his precious Side, that might the ſooner expire his Life; or, rather, from all together. Yet <hi>finding him already dead, they broke not his Legs:</hi> Or chiefly to fulfil the fore-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate Will of the Almighty pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted and propheſied of him, <hi>That a Bone of him ſhould not be broken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as we ſee all along from the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, and all-wiſe Counſel of Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and from the unalterable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Omniſciency, nothing could from his Conception to his Crucifixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, happen to him, but what was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably neceſſary and foretold, that
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:110425:61"/>it might be of Belief to perſuade one, of the True <hi>Meſſias;</hi> and of Infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to obdurate the other: For ſo ſays the Great Apoſtle, <hi>I preach Chriſt Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, to the Jews a Stumbling Block, and unto us Gentiles, the Life and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God unto Salvation,</hi> for they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did, nor yet will, believe the Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuality of the Son of God in this World; but ſtill are vainly in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Joſeph</hi> being <hi>a juſt man,</hi> and altho' one of the Jews, yet had no hand in conſenting to the Death of the Son of God, went in privately, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Jews, becauſe he was of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> a City of the Jews, but <hi>went boldly unto</hi> Pilate, <hi>and begg'd the Body of Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>when Even was come, becauſe it was the Preparation Even before the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> Joſeph <hi>of</hi> Arimathea, <hi>an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Counſellor, who alſo himſelf waited for the Kingdom of God, came and went in boldly to</hi> Pilate, <hi>and crav'd the Body of Jeſus.</hi> But <hi>Pilate</hi> fill'd with Incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity, marvell'd <hi>if he ſhould be already dead:</hi> And, to be fully ſatisfied, ſends
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:110425:61"/>for the Centurion, whom he had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ſtand by, and ſee the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution done, and ask'd, If <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth</hi> was dead, and <hi>whether he had been any time dead,</hi> and when the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion told him, that he was dead, for his Body the Soldiers had already (with his leave,) taken down from the Croſs, and they had broke the Legs of the other two: But when they came to <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> he they <hi>found al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready dead, and therefore his Legs were not broken. When Pilate heard all this, he commanded the Body of Jeſus to be given to Joſeph,</hi> Mark 15.42, 46<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Matth. 27.58.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Joſeph took him away, and wrapp'd his Body in Sindon, or new fine Linen Cloth; and alſo Nicodemus, which, at the firſt, came to Jeſus by night, and brought a mixture of Myrrh, Aloes, and other Spices, as the Cuſtom of the Jews was, and wrapp'd him up in fine Linnen, ready for his Funeral,</hi> which was to be ſolemniz'd this Evening in the Garden of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> a place without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and near to the place where our Saviour was Crucified, and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:110425:62"/>in a <hi>new Tomb hewed out of a Rock,</hi> that <hi>Joſeph</hi> had made for himſelf, and <hi>where never Man lay before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, O my Soul, prepare thy ſelf, with all Humility and Devotion, to attend thy Lord and Saviour to his Funeral. This is the laſt Office of Love thou haſt to perform to the dear Body of thy departed <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who had done and ſuffer'd ſo much for thee.</p>
            <p>O my Soul! what an honour it is to thee to be eſteem'd worthy by thy Lord to be bid a Mourner at his Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral?</p>
            <p>And happy and bleſſed art thou, O <hi>Joſeph,</hi> that thou waſt waiting impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently patient for the Body of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and for the Kingdom of God. O hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py art thou, that, in this black and diſmal night of ſorrow, thy Faith fail'd thee not, and that thy tranſcendent Love to thy Jeſu carry'd thee through all fears and difficulties of the <hi>Jews,</hi> to crave the Body of <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was love indeed, that at ſuch a time as this was, while the rage and malice of the <hi>Jews</hi> was ſtill boiling hot in them, and ſeeing all his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:110425:62"/>had left him before this Day of Trial, thou might'ſt reaſonably have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that their remaining rage might have ſpent it ſelf upon them, that ſhould have ſhewn any manner of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Remaining Body of a Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify'd <hi>Jeſus.</hi> Yet true Faith carry'd thee beyond fear; come Life, come Death, nothing can or ſhall ſeparate a true <hi>Joſeph,</hi> a truly devout Soul, from the Love of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Yet, withal, we may from hence ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Prudence and Care a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ought to have: He went privately, in reſpect of the <hi>Jews,</hi> whoſe precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate rage had ſo lately embru'd their hands in the Blood of an Innocent, harmleſs, <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and was ſtill reeking hot with that Cruelty; but yet boldly, in reſpect of <hi>Pilate, he went in, and begg'd the Body of Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Love and Faith to <hi>Jeſus</hi> made him bold, but his Wiſdom and Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made him cautions; If he muſt ſacrifice his Life for his Love to his Saviour, it ſhould be by the hands of a Legiſlative Power, and not by the mercileſs barbarity of the Mobile;
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:110425:63"/>but, if it muſt be ſo, ready and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd he was immediately to follow, and be ſecond to ſo good a Saviour, for whoſe Salvation he had ſo long time waited.</p>
            <p>O Bleſſed <hi>Joſeph!</hi> Had'ſt not thou took care of the Son of God, of <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> the King of the <hi>Jews,</hi> of the ever-bleſſed <hi>Jeſu,</hi> Redeemer, and Saviour of the World, to have given him decent Burial, his Sacred Body might have laid all mangled, torn, diſtorted, and extended upon the cold Earth to the mercileſs Cruelty and ſavage Nature of Wild Beaſts, and Birds of Prey. But this was deſign'd from all Eternity, that thou ſhould'ſt be the Man appointed by the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatick Counſel of Heaven; I ſay, to be the Man to embalm and entomb the Body of the ever-bleſſed <hi>Jeſus;</hi> and for this art thou ſure, to have thy Soul embrac'd and enthron'd in Heaven in the Boſom of thy Saviour. <hi>He that is not aſham'd to confeſs and own me before Men,</hi> in the moſt dangerous of times, <hi>him will I not be aſham'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs and own before my Father which is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:110425:63"/>And now Even is come, and the time of Solemnity and Entombing of our Saviour is at hand; away now, my Soul, with all the heavy weight and burthen of thy Sins, to the Grave of thy Saviour.</p>
            <p>The Body born by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, vailing their Faces,<note place="margin">The Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of our Saviours Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</note> who, in the time of his Humanity, were always appointed by God to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon him, and miniſter unto him, and alſo, while in the Grave, to perform the ſame Heavenly Office. And <hi>there appear'd two Angels ſitting. the one at the head, and the other at the feet:</hi> And can we think, they ſhould be ſpar'd or wanted at this time? <hi>Luke</hi> 24.4. <hi>John</hi> 20.12.</p>
            <p>Firſt, follow'd by <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea,</hi> and <hi>Nicodemus, John</hi> 16.39.40. Then <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of the ever-bleſſed <hi>Jeſus, Mary Magdalen,</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Joſes,</hi> and the Mother of <hi>Zebedee</hi>'s Children. And the Women that follow'd after, as Mourners, <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>held the Body where if
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:110425:64"/>was laid, Luke</hi> 23.55. And all the reſt of the Mourners came following after, ordered by the great Herauld of Heaven. And <hi>I will in that day pour upon the houſe of</hi> David <hi>and Inhabitants of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>the Spirit of Grace and Supplication, and they ſhall look upon me, whom they have perceiv'd, and they ſhall mourn for him, as one that mourneth for his only begotten Son, and ſhall be in bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs for him, as one that is in bitterneſs for his firſt-horn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In that day there ſhall be a very great mourning in</hi> Jeruſalem,<note place="margin">Typically ſpoke of good <hi>Joſiah</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Saviour at this time, <hi>Rev. 1.7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>as the mourning of</hi> Haddadrimon <hi>in the Valley of</hi> Megiddon: <hi>And the Land ſhall mourn, every Family apart. The Family of the Houſe of</hi> David <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and their Wives apart. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the Houſe of</hi> Nathan <hi>apart, and their Wives apart. The Family of the Houſe of</hi> Live <hi>apart, and their Wives a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part. The Family of</hi> Shimei, <hi>and their Wives apart. And all the Families that remain; every Family apart, and their Wives apart,</hi> Zech. 12.10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:110425:64"/>Come now, O my Soul, do thee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after; gather up, I ſay, all thy Sins from the ſoot of the Croſs, and bring them with thee to the Grave of thy Saviour. Bury them there in a Flood of Tears, with the reſt of thoſe Afflicted Mourners, that they may never riſe up in this World more to affright thee, nor in the World to come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thee. Leave them all there, that they may all be laid <hi>upon the head of the ſcape-Goat, and carry'd into the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> the Land of forgetfulneſs.</p>
            <p>And now ſtrengthen your Heads, you weak Hearts, and gather ſtrength, ye feeble Knees, for now is your Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion near at hand. <hi>And they roll'd a great ſtone to the door of the Sepulchre, and departed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus having as ſuccinctly, as poſſibly I could, run over the Paſſion of our Dear Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, in that method and order the Holy Scriptures have moſt perſpicuouſly teſtify'd of him, both by the Prophets, and alſo the Apoſtles, I ſhall conclude all with that of the moſt Holy Apoſtle, and, for the preſent, leave his precious Body in the Grave, with Angles to attend his
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:110425:65"/>Call to his Glorious Reſurrection, which the bleſſed Apoſtle, in theſe few words, proclaims.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye Men of</hi> Iſrael! <hi>Hear theſe words, Jeſus of Nazareth, a Man approv'd of God among you by Miracles, Wonders, and Signs, which God did by him in the midſt of ye, as ye your ſelves alſo know. Him, being deliver'd by the determinate Counſel and foreknowledge of God, ye have taken, and by wicked hands have crucify'd and ſlain. Whom God hath rais'd up, having loos'd the Pains of Death, becauſe it was not poſſible that he ſhould be holden of it. But</hi> David <hi>ſpeaketh concerning him, I foreſaw the Lord always before my Face, for he is on my Right hand that I ſhould not be mov'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore did my Heart rejoyce, and my Tongue was glad, moreover alſo my Fleſh ſhall reſt in hope, becauſe thou wilt not leave my Soul in Hell, neither wilt thou ſuffer thy Holy One to ſee Corruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou haſt made known to me the way of Life, and thou ſhalt make me full of Joy with thy Countenance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Glory to God on High, Peace on Earth, Good Will towards Men.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="meditations">
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:110425:65"/>
            <head>Meditations and Ejaculations to be uſed in thy Cloſet, before, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately at, the Table of the Lord, or after thou art return'd into thy Cloſet again; Made and compos'd by the Author, from the Conſiderations of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, by his <hi>Body, Blood,</hi> and <hi>Interceſſion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>O Lord! help the Sluces of my Soul to pour out Tears abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, for my many Sins, heinous Sins, great and grievous Sins. O Lord, help me! O Chriſt, help me! O Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the World, help me. O Lamb of God, help me! O Redeemer of the World, help me! O dear, and ever bleſſed, Jeſu, Chriſt, and Saviour, help me! I fear, I ſhall be drein'd dry too ſoon: I fear, I ſhall ſlacken too faſt. Help me, Lord, to a River of Tears, that I may pour out more, more, O penſive Heart and Soul; more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:110425:66"/>my Heart and Soul, to my God. This is Pleaſure indeed; This is Joy unexpreſſible, thus to be thorowly, perfectly, and fully, employ'd in the Service of my God, for my poor Souls ſake.</p>
            <p>This is the only Viand for my Soul to feed upon: This is the Bread, my Soul (O Heavenly Father!) eats, that the World knows not of. This is the only Wine, that cheers and makes glad the Heart of Man. This is the only Cordial for my fainting and drooping Soul. This is the true Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Laver of Life to my Soul. This fetches out all Spots and Stains, all Pollutions and Crimes, of never ſo deep a Die, of never ſo long a Time, of never ſo large an Extenſion, never ſo remote in the World, never ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and cloſely committed.</p>
            <p>Theſe thy Cloſet-Tears, and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental-Tears, mixt with the Blood of thy dying Crucify'd Saviour,<note place="margin">The compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of this Heavenly Laver.</note> will waſh and fetch all out. This is the only Elixir of Life. This maſters the ſtrongeſt Luſts, the greateſt Temptations. This
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:110425:66"/>is of ſuch Power and Force. O Lord, that all the Devils in Hell, compact and conjoyn'd together, muſt give way to. This unties all Charms and Witchcrafts, Powers and Compacts, of Infernal Spirits. This diſſolves and breaks in pieces all that a wicked Heart, murtherous Hand, an incenſed Enemy, and an enraged Devil can do. This Cordial, this Laver alone, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports the Soul, and makes it live, even in Death it ſelf: Whether of the moſt exquiſit Pain of the Croſs, or the Rack, or Fleaing alive, or Boiling in Oil, or Roaſting alive, Breaking on the Wheel, or tearing in ſunder with Wild Beaſts; let it be of what Nature, Degree, or Quality ſoever. This Cordial bears the Soul up above the Cruelty, Rage and Malice, that the worſt of Men, or Devils, can invent. Nay further, if this be rightly taken, and made uſe of, it appeaſes the Wrath of an incenſed, enraged, and, otherwiſe irreconcilea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, God.</p>
            <p>O Heavenly Father! this thou canſt not withſtand, ſo great Force and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er have Cloſet-Prayers; and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental-Prayers, One hour, ſpent thus
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:110425:67"/>cloſely in Communion with God, is worth Ten thouſand elſewhere Theſe Prayers and Tears force open the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Doors of Heaven it ſelf: And an enraged God cannot, nay, will not, longer, hold out. A Saviour, a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, an Advocate, ſo dear and ſo near a Friend in Heaven, will prevall for us. And from this time our Names ſhall be Recorded in Heaven, and written in the Book of Life in Red Characters of our Saviour's Blood, over every one of our Manſions he hath already prepar'd for us.</p>
            <p>This is certainly the Security of our Souls, againſt all Accidents of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, againſt Battels and Murthers, and againſt ſuddain Death; againſt Fits of the Stone, Diſtortions, Convulſions, Twiſting of the Guts, and the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Torment of the Bowels; againſt Palſies, Lethargies, Apoplexies, and all Deprivings of the natural Senſes.</p>
            <p>The countinued courſe of theſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,<note place="margin">A Soul thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd and guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is defended againſt all theſe Accidents and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers of the Body, that may ſuddainly deprive us of our Senſe and Reaſon, before, or when Death comes.</note> is the only Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote againſt ſcorching
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:110425:67"/>and burning Feavers. This preſerves thee againſt, and in, decrepit Old Age, and decay, and loſs of Senſes and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Reaſon. This preſerves thee from, and in, Bonds and Impriſonment, Storms, Tempeſts, and Shipwracks; againſt all Caſualties and Afflictions, Anguiſh and Tortures of the Body; and (being effectually apply'd) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Wounds of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>This Temper of Soul, and Intereſt in a Crucify'd Saviour, makes one to grow (O Lord!) quickly weary of the World, and to ſlight and contemn all Earthly Delights. This makes thee earneſtly <hi>long to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt.</hi> This will make thee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult upon, and trample under, all Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatities and Powers, all Thrones and Dominions, and deſire no longer to live: than thou canſt be thus diſpos'd, qualify'd and employ'd. This will make thee (O my Soul!) to do no Evil, nor think any Evil with Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Conſent.</p>
            <p>The Soul, O Lord! may, and will be impos'd upon by the Body daily, in one degree or other; but what I do, I allow not. My Eyes, my Ears,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:110425:68"/>my Noſe, my Tongue, my Smell, my Taſt, my Hands, and my Feet, they all aſſault daily my yoor Soul, in one way or manner or other, and let in a <hi>Caterva</hi> of Sins and Temptations, and are Cauſe, O Lord, of this <hi>Pſycoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia,</hi> War between Soul and Body, which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> too well knew, and made his complain of, ſaying, <hi>I have a Will in my Members, that Wars againſt the Will of my Mind, and leads me Captivate unto Sin and Death. O wretched Man that I am!</hi> One look from they Heavenly Eye, dear Saviour, or one Glimpſe of thee, one hour of Cloſet-Devotion, or Sacramental-De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, will make me <hi>more than Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror</hi> over all, and ſay again, with the Apoſtle, <hi>Thanks be to God through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is all that a poor Soul can do, or that God doth require of thee, ſtrong Prayers and Tears, mixt with the Body and Blood of thy Saviour, is all thou art able to give for Heaven it ſelf.</p>
            <p>He that calleth, cryeth, weepeth, mourneth, and cometh thus to me, I will in no wiſe caſt out. This is all that God doth require of thee, <hi>To do
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:110425:68"/>Juſtice, love Mercy, and walk humbly before thy God.</hi> This ſhall ſeal the Bonds of the everlaſting Covenant between God and my Soul, written in my precious Saviour's Blood; and he himſelf ſhall be a ſtanding and an abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Witneſs to each Covenant; (<hi>and I will make with thee an everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, the ſure Mercies of David,</hi>) and himſelf ſhall be my Advocate, to plead my Title to <hi>an Inheritance incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, that fadeth not away,</hi> reſerv'd in Heaven for me, O my Soul. If any Man ſin, <hi>we have an Advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous,</hi> dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly making interceſſion for us.</p>
            <p>When thou art Meditating, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or Reading thus, my Soul! take not thy Eye, nor thy Heart, off, but go on with it; thy God is at the end of it, Heaven is at the end of it, and thy Redeemer is at the end of it. This is thy <hi>Viaticum.</hi> This is <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thou art aſcending. It's the ſure and certain way to Heaven and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life.</p>
            <p>This is my Saviour's Advice; and I dare, and will, put thee, my Soul, upon the Dependence and Aſſurance of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:110425:69"/>it. Ten thouſand to one for thy Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. <hi>Enter into thy Cloſet, ſhut the Door about thee, and Pray</hi> (in this manner already propos'd,) ſtrongly and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, <hi>to thy Father in private, and he will reward thee openly;</hi> That is, give thee, my Soul, all things neceſſary for thee in this World, and in the World to come everlaſting Life.</p>
            <p>O my Soul, when once thou art come to taſt this Heavenly Food, and reliſh it aright, this Cordial of Life, what Sweetneſs, what pleaſures, and what Delights doth it bing! O Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, and ever bleſſed Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, this Laver alone, to waſh and rince my polluted Soul in, will make it fit to be preſented to the Lamb upon the Throne, <hi>without Spot, or Wrinkle, or any ſuch thing;</hi> And this I beg with all Humility and Devotion, that I am able to do, upon the Account, and for the Sake of my ever Bleſſed Redeemer and Advocate, concluding in that Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prayer He Himſelf hath taught me, ſaying, <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:110425:69"/>
            <head>A Prayer for the Author or Reader.</head>
            <p>O Lord! aſſiſt me ſo with Thy Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit, that all that I have now Written or Read in this foregoing Work, may always be freſh upon my Heart and Soul; and grant me, O God, that at this time, I may pour out my Soul unto Thee upon my bended Knees, in ſuch like Prayers and Supplications that may be prevalent with Thee, my Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to guard and defend me this Day from all manner of Sins and power of Temptations whatſoever. More eſpecially againſt all thoſe Sins that do ſo eaſie beſet me, and meet me at every turn; thoſe Sins thou knoweſt, O Heavenly Father, are my familiar and prevailing Sins, that now by the ſpecial Concurrence of thy Bleſſed Spirit, I may be able to ſtrike at the very root of them all, and, like <hi>David,</hi> kill the <hi>Goliah.</hi> Give me, O Lord, a true rectify'd Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Sanctify'd throughout to overcome all Infirmities and Corruptions of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature. And that I may betake my ſelf ſincerely to the great Buſineſs
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:110425:70"/>of the Salvation of my Soul. And that, with the Bleſſed Apoſtle, <hi>I may run the Race that is ſet before me, looking unto Chriſt Jeſus the Author and Finiſher of my Faith, who, for the Joy that was ſet before him, endur'd the Croſs, deſpis'd the ſhame, and now is ſet at the Right Hand of God, daily to make Interceſſion</hi> for me. For <hi>him,</hi> O Heavenly Father, <hi>haſt thou high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exalted, and given him a Name above all other Names, that at the Name of Jeſus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Knee ſhould how, both of things in Heaven, and of things on Earth.</hi> O ſweet Jeſu, O bleſſed Jeſu, who can but bow to Thee, and ſupplicate to Thee, and pour out their Prayers and Tears to Thee, that left the boſom of Thy Father, and all the Adorations and Chorus's of Saints and Angels, and came down from Heaven to ſuffer the curſed and ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Death of the Croſs for my Sins; to have thy tender Hands, that were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways doing of Good, and healing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes; and thy bleſſed Feet that always kept the ſteady Paths of Eternal Life, now to be turn'd, twiſted, extended, diſtorted, disjointed, and Nail'd to the Croſs, to drink the Vinegar and Gaul of Thy Father's high Diſpleaſure, for my
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:110425:70"/>great and grievous Sins, to have Thy moſt ſacred Sides pierc'd, and to guſh out with Water and Blood. To ſee Thee all over ſweating, and pouring down Streams of Blood from the Crown of Thy Head to the Foot of the Croſs, and to ſuffer all this for my great, grievous, hainous, Sins, and abominable Iniquities.</p>
            <p>Nay further, O Dear Jeſu, to ſee Thee endure, and to lie under Thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Wrath, and the preſſure of all theſe Agonies and Torments, which made Thee bitterly to cry out, <hi>My God, my God, Why haſt thou forſaken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Lord! What ſhall I do? Who is able to behold Thee longer? Who can but love Thee, and in loving Thee, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore Thee, with infinite, unbounded, and unmeaſurable Love, and deſire earneſtly to be Diſſolved, and to be with Thee? But if it is Thy good Pleaſure to ſpare me longer, let the true Love and perfect ſenſe of all this Love and Suffering of Thine, my Dear Lord and Saviour, help me to live up to that exact Pattern thou haſt left me here of Meekneſs, Lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Humility, Charity, Forgiveneſs, Bowels of Pity, and Compaſſion, and that a perfect ſenſe of Thy Crucifixion,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:110425:71"/>may always be freſh in my Heart and Soul, that ſo it may beget in me a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat hatred and dread of all Sins; that, in the whole Courſe of my remaining Life, I may be preſerved and defended from the like Sins, that I run not the danger of Eternal Damnation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And that the inexhauſtible Bowels of Thy Mercy may take pity of me, ſo that I Crucifie Thee not again, but, being delivered from all Iniquities, by thy moſt mighty Power, may, with finiſhing my Courſe here, be receiv'd into the open Arms of Thy Eternal Salvation. And this I moſt heartily beg upon the bended Knees of my Soul, for Thy ſake only, and upon the alone account of Thee, my Dear Lord and Saviour, and ever-bleſſed Redeemer and Advocate. <hi>Amen,</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="meditation">
            <head>A Death Bed Meditation.</head>
            <p>I Owe to God a Death, as his Son did for me. Ever ſince I have been born I have been ſailing to this Haven, and gathering Patience to comfort me in this Hour; therefore ſhould I be one
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:110425:71"/>of thoſe Gueſts, that would not come to the Banquet, when they were invited? What hurt is there is going to Sleep? In going to Paradiſe? I ſhall loſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the Senſe of Evils, and anon I ſhall have greater Joys than I feel Pains, for my Head is in Heaven al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, to aſſure me, my Soul and Body ſhall follow after. <hi>O Death! Where is thy Sting?</hi> Why ſhould I fear that, which I would not eſcape, becauſe my chief Happineſs is gone before, and I cannot have it, unleſs I go to it? I would even go through Hell it ſelf for Heaven: and therefore, if I march but through Death, I ſuffer leſs than I would for God.</p>
            <p>My Pains do not diſmay me, becauſe I Travel to bring forth Eternal Life. My Sins do not fright me, becauſe I have Chriſt my Redeemer there. The Judge doth not aſtoniſh me, becauſe I have the Judges Son my Advocate. The Devil amazes me not, becauſe the Angels pitch their Tents about me. The Grave grieves me not, becauſe I know it was my Lord's Bed. O, that God's Mercy to me might move others to love him: For the leſs I can expreſs of it, the more it is.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:110425:72"/>The Prophets, and the Apoſtles, are my Fore-runners; every Man will go before, or follow after. If it pleaſe God to receive me into Heaven, before them that ſerv'd him better, what Thankfulneſs do I owe him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have deferr'd my Repentance till this Hour, whereby my Salvation had been cut off, had I dy'd ſuddenly?</p>
            <p>How doth my God, in his Infinite Mercy, to prevent my Deſtruction, call me by this lingring Sickneſs, and prepares me for my End, and makes me, by wholſome Pains, weary of this beloved World; leſt I ſhould depart unwillingly, like to thoſe, whoſe Death is their Damnation.</p>
            <p>Thus he loves me while he beats me, and his Stripes are Plaiſters to cure my Sores; therefore, who ſhall love him, if I diſpleaſe him? This is my whole Buſineſs now, to ſtrengthen my Body with my Heart, and to be contented as God hath appointed, until I can Glorify him, or He me. If I live, I live to Sacrifice; If I dye, I dye to my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; for Chriſt my Saviour is Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed for me, and therefore ſhould I fear Death, I have not that Faith and
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:110425:72"/>Hope I have profeſs'd, but I doubted of God's Truth in his Promiſes: Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no he will forgive Penitent Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, (which I ſear not,) <hi>Come, Lord Jeſus,</hi> for now thy Servant cometh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Everlaſting Arms of Mercy. I commit my Soul into thy Hands, O Heavenly Father; <hi>Come, Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter written to his Friend in his Sickneſs.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Marvelled not, that you have Pain, for you are Sick; but I marvel that you cover it not, for Offences; becauſe the Wiſdom of Man is to bite in his Gpief, and always to ſhew more Comfort in God, than Pain in Suffering. Now God calleth to Repetitious, to ſee whether you have learn'd more Patience, and Conſtancy than others. If Sickneſs be ſharp, make it not more ſharp by frowardneſs: But know, this is a great Favour to us, when we dye by Sickneſs, that makes us ready for God when he calls us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:110425:73"/>Now you have nothing to think upon but God, and you cannot think upon him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Joy: Your Grief paſſes away, but your Joy will never. Tell me, Friend, or Patient, How many Stripes is Heaven worth? Is my Friend only Sick in the World, or his Faith weaker than others? You have always Pray'd, <hi>Thy Will be done,</hi> and are you now offended, that <hi>God's Will</hi> is done? How hath the Faithful Man forgot, that all things, (even Death if ſelf) turn to the beſt, to them that love God?</p>
            <p>Teach the Happy, O Lord, to ſee his Happineſs through Troubles. Every Pain is the prevention of the Pain of Hell: Every Eaſe, in Pain, is a fore-taſt of the Eaſe, and Peace, and Joys, in Heaven. Remember therefore your own Comforts to others before, and be not impatient, when there is moſt need of Patience; but, as you have ever Taught us to Live, ſo now give us an Example to Dye, and deceive <hi>Satan,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> did.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:110425:73"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
